<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A monument of remembrance erected in Albion, in honor of the magnificent departure from Britannie, and honorable receiuing in Germany, namely at Heidelberge, of the two most noble princes Fredericke, first prince of the imperiall bloud, sprung from glorious Charlemaigne, Count Palatine of Rhine, Duke of Bauier, Elector and Arch-sewer of the holy Romane Empire, and Knight of the renowned order of the Garter. &amp; Elizabeth Infanta of Albion, Princess Palatine, and Dutchesse of Bauier, the onely daughter of our most gratious and soueraigne Lord Charles-Iames, and of his most noble and vertuous wife, Queene Anne. Both of them being almost in one and the same degree lineall descent from 25 emperours of the east and west, of Romanes, Greekes, and Germans, and from 30 kings of diuers countries. By Iames Maxvvel.</title>
            <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847794</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12855</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A monument of remembrance erected in Albion, in honor of the magnificent departure from Britannie, and honorable receiuing in Germany, namely at Heidelberge, of the two most noble princes Fredericke, first prince of the imperiall bloud, sprung from glorious Charlemaigne, Count Palatine of Rhine, Duke of Bauier, Elector and Arch-sewer of the holy Romane Empire, and Knight of the renowned order of the Garter. &amp; Elizabeth Infanta of Albion, Princess Palatine, and Dutchesse of Bauier, the onely daughter of our most gratious and soueraigne Lord Charles-Iames, and of his most noble and vertuous wife, Queene Anne. Both of them being almost in one and the same degree lineall descent from 25 emperours of the east and west, of Romanes, Greekes, and Germans, and from 30 kings of diuers countries. By Iames Maxvvel.</title>
                  <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Henry Bell, and are to be sold at his shop within Bishops-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Mostly in verse.</note>
                  <note>The words "Fredericke .. Garter." and "Elizabeth .. Queene Anne." are bracketed in two columnms, separated by the ampersand.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ a⁴ B-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elizabeth, --  Queen, consort of Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1662 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MONVMENT of Remembrance, ERECTED IN ALBION, IN HONOR OF THE MAGNIFICENT DEPARTVRE FROM BRITANNIE, and honorable receiuing in GERMANY, namely at HEIDELBERGE, of the <hi>two moſt Noble Princes</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>FREDERICKE,</hi> Firſt Prince of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall bloud, ſprung from glorious <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaigne, Count Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> of <hi>Rhine,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> Elector and Arch-ſewer of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, and Knight of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned order of the GARTER. &amp;</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> INFANTA of AL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BION, Princeſſe PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATINE, and Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of BAVIER, the onely Daughter of our moſt gratious and Soueraigne Lord CHARLES-IAMES, and of his moſt Noble and vertuous Wife, Queene ANNE.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Both of them being almoſt in one and the ſame degree of lineall deſcent from</hi> 25 <hi>Emperours of the Eaſt and Weſt, of</hi> Romanes, Greekes, <hi>and</hi> Germans, <hi>and from</hi> 30 <hi>Kings of diuers countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By IAMES MAXVVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> for <hi>Henry Bell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop within Biſhops-gate. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="historical_summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Summary view of the Hiſtoricall</hi> Points, and Poeticall Conceits occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>in this preſent Monument.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THAT Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> is in one and the ſame degree of deſcent with our moſt gracious Soueraigne <hi>IAMES</hi> the <hi>Concorder,</hi> from <hi>20</hi> Emperours of Romans, Greekes, and Germanes, and from <hi>24</hi> Kings of diuers countries.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> That Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> is in one and the ſame degree of deſcent with our moſt noble Queene <hi>ANNE,</hi> from foure Emperours, and three Kings.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> That Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> is in one &amp; the ſame degree of deſcent with Princeſſe <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> his ſpouſe, from one Emperour, and eight Kings, of diuers countries, beſides the former.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> That Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> is deſcended from <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Elder, Edmund Ironſide, Henry</hi> the <hi>1.</hi> and <hi>2.</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and likewiſe from <hi>Malcolme Cammore</hi> King of Scotland.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> That Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> &amp; Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> brothers in Law, are collinially deſcended from two borne brothers, to wit, <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> being the elder, from <hi>Henry</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Saxe,</hi> who was likewiſe the elder of the ſaid two brothers: and Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> being the yonger, from the yonger brother <hi>Otho,</hi> once Earle of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Emperour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> That the Pope did preſumptuouſly and wickedly abuſe <hi>Otho</hi> Earle of <hi>Yorke</hi> and Emperour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> That there haue been as yet, but onely two Emperours of the <hi>Palatine</hi> family, the one a yonger brother, named <hi>Lodowicke,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12855:3"/>Duke of <hi>Bauiere;</hi> the other an elder brother named <hi>Robert,</hi> Count Palatine: and that from both of them, and their Empreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Margaret</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are lineally deſcended.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> That the ſaid two Emperours, choſen of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Family, haue had an exceeding different Fortune in their acceptance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Pope, the one being highly hated of three euill <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinion</hi>-Popes; the other as highly beloued of one good <hi>Rome-Pope.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> That the Palatine Princes haue beene very officious at all times to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and their children: namely in electing ſome of them to be Emperours, hoping that they ſhall yet hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proue more officious and forward in the ſame kinde, then euer they haue done before.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> That our moſt gratious Soueraigne, by the meanes of the moſt Illuſtrious houſe of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> is lineally deſcended, as from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the German Emperours, ſo from one who was both Prince Palatine, and Emperour, named <hi>Robert the Noble:</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that being both of the Germane and Imperiall bloud, that he is capable of the Imperiall dignity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> That <hi>Albions</hi> Iſland, though it be her fortune to bee deflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of two flowres in one yeare, a <hi>Lilly</hi> and a <hi>Roſe,</hi> yet muſt ſhe not be altogether diſcouraged, ſo long as there remaineth a <hi>Lilly-Roſe</hi> behind.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> That there haue beene diuers matchings of the daughters of this Iſland with forraigne Princes, namely of <hi>Germany, France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the cauſe why they haue beene all iſſuleſſe and fruitleſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> That there haue beene three diuers <hi>Vnion-endeauours</hi> of three <hi>Maries,</hi> of three diuers countries, <hi>Engliſh, French</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh;</hi> and that the third <hi>Mary</hi> was ſhee, who with <hi>Mary</hi> in the Goſpell did chooſe the better part.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> That of this late Alliance is to bee expected an <hi>Vnion</hi> of <hi>Northerne Princes,</hi> long agoe fore-told, (as ſhall bee ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in our <hi>Sibylla Britannica</hi>) whereby the <hi>Turke</hi> muſt bee totally ouer-throwne; and that, as ſome haue thought,
<pb facs="tcp:12855:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>neere the Riuer of <hi>Rhine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> That among all the <hi>Propheſies</hi> or <hi>Predictions</hi> that doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe any glorious exploit to be brought to paſſe by any Prince, not as yet fulfilled, that is the moſt notable which hath beene vttered concerning a Prince of the name of <hi>Charles;</hi> with the Authors ardent wiſh for Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> which is more fully expreſſed is a Poëme vpon his hopefull <hi>Natiuity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> That peereleſſe Prince <hi>Henry</hi> ſeemeth to inuite and adiure all the Worthies of <hi>Britannie,</hi> by their moſt ardent loue towards him dead and aliue, to glorifie the day of his deere ſiſters depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for <hi>Germany,</hi> that her day may bee as celebrious as euer <hi>Gonilda's</hi> was, and more.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> That <hi>Iaſons Sydereall ſhip,</hi> which once fetcht from <hi>Colchos</hi> to <hi>Greece</hi> the <hi>Golden Fleece,</hi> looketh as if ſhe did deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from her ſtarry Hauen into our <hi>Thames,</hi> thence to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the <hi>Golden Fleece</hi> of <hi>IAMES.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> That <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> thoſe two louing <hi>Twinnes,</hi> borne in <hi>Aprill</hi> to baniſh <hi>Pyracie,</hi> doe looke downe from their ſtarry <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> as if they meaned to grace and guard <hi>ELIZA'S Argo,</hi> named <hi>Prince-Henry,</hi> till ſhe be ſafely arriued at the <hi>Shore</hi> of <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> That <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> or the <hi>Coeleſtiall Virgine,</hi> vnder whoſe ſigne <hi>ELIZA</hi> was borne, and likewiſe Prince <hi>FREDERICKE;</hi> and who hath beene ſo liberall of her beſt influences in her Gracefull behalfe, (as may appeare more amply by our Poëme made vpon her <hi>Natiuity</hi>) commands two of her greateſt lights to attend <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liza</hi> to her ſhip, and to light her ſo many nights as ſhe ſhall chance to ſtay vpon the ſea.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> That <hi>Aeolus, Neptunus, Tethys,</hi> and <hi>Doris,</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Marinall powers,</hi> endeauour each of them to doe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liza</hi> ſome good office: the one perfuming the aire with Muskie-breath for her ſake; the others calming and ſweetning the Seas for her ſake.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> That the louing <hi>Dolphins</hi> deſire to flocke about <hi>Eliza's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> with many demonſtrations of greateſt ioy, both for her owne ſake, and for her <hi>Grandames</hi> ſake, who was once a <hi>Dolphins</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12855:4"/>deereſt deere, with Historicall examples of their reſcuing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons from Sea-danger.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> That <hi>Rhine</hi> begins to reuell for ioy of <hi>Elizaes</hi> arviuall, and the admirable nature thereof, in diſcerning of ſuch barnes as haue beene gotten with falſe play.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> That <hi>Cybele</hi> the mother of the Gods, that is, of Kings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was the firſt Queene-mother in the world, together with <hi>Flora</hi> Queene of <hi>May,</hi> are both of them buſied in contriuing of Aprill-carpets, and May-coronets, and Flowry-pearly-ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopies in honour of <hi>Eliza,</hi> the one to lay along vnder her feet, the other to hang and beare aboue her head at her entrie to <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> That the ſyluane <hi>Pan,</hi> together with the daintie Nymph <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ope,</hi> are both gone to <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> to fetch a Marriage-may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole for our <hi>Palatine-paire,</hi> of two louing Palme-trees: and of the wonderfull loue that Hiſtories do record to be betweene the Palmes, male and female.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> That the three Graces reſembling the three faces of three famous Brittiſh Queenes, ſuted in three diuers colours, are to preſent <hi>Eliza</hi> with three Roſes of three diuers kindes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> That the Mirtle-nymph of <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> mounted vpon her crowned Lion, is to meet our Roſie Nymph at the Citties-gate, to do their ſeuerall obeyſances; with diuers notable things of the nature and Armes of the Lion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> That the fragrant Mirtle-tree of <hi>Egypt</hi> is due to <hi>Eliza,</hi> no leſſe then the Mirtle-berry-hill of <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> with the crowned Lion thereof, as being of the Royall <hi>Egyptian</hi> bloud of <hi>Oſiris, Iſis,</hi> and <hi>Hercules,</hi> who firſt bare the Lion in his Armes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28</hi> That <hi>Eliza</hi> is another <hi>Myrſina,</hi> who for her worth was once <hi>Mineruaes</hi> deere.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> That the Matrons and Maids of <hi>Heidelberge</hi> ſhall praiſe <hi>Eliza</hi> aboue all the daughters of Emperours and Kings that haue beene married to their Princes in former times, and that the Muſes there are to doe as much, ſome in Poeſie, and other ſome in proſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> That the Church-Holy-Ghoſt of <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> founded by
<pb facs="tcp:12855:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Prince Palatine, and Emperour <hi>Robert,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Empreſſe, ſhall exceedingly reioyce at <hi>Elizabeths</hi> entry, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withall, that ſhee could ſing as ſweetly as doth <hi>Londons S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls</hi> by the mouth of her Organ-quire of ſurpliſed ſinging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for ſweet <hi>Elizabeths</hi> ſake.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> That vpon <hi>Pantheon</hi> hill, hard by <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> the moſt renowned Perſian Princeſſe <hi>Panthaea,</hi> is to preſent <hi>Eliza</hi> ſprung from a <hi>Panthaea,</hi> with a Lilly-garland made of ſuch ſweet Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies as do grow about her Lilly-citty of <hi>Suſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> That <hi>Panthaea</hi> is to bee honoured of all Matrones and wiues, as their Patroneſſe, moſt worthy of imitation: and that her deere <hi>Abradate</hi> ought to ſerue for a Patrone and patterne vnto all husbands of louing their wiues deerely, and thinking alwayes of them worthily; with diuers notable examples of the fond iealouſie of ſome husbands, how that it hath turned highly to their harme, ſhame, and higheſt diſhonour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> That vpon <hi>S. Abrahams</hi> hill, hard by <hi>Heidelberge, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> ſeeme to meet <hi>Fredericke</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whom they bleſſe with the bleſſings of <hi>Iſaac and Rebecca, Iacob</hi> and <hi>Rahel,</hi> wiſhing they may long liue in higheſt honour, beſides <hi>S. Abrahams</hi> hill on earth; and in the end be tranſlated gloriouſly to <hi>S. Abrahams</hi> boſome, and Gods holy hill in heauen. Which is likewiſe the ardent wiſh of their right denoted and humble ſeruant.</item>
            </list>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iames Maxwell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE RIGHT ILLVSTRIOVS HOVSE OF HOWARDS, HONORED <hi>WITH THE CONFLVENCE</hi> OF TWO AND FOVRTY STREAMES OF PRINCELY BLOVD, DERIVED FROM TWELVE IMPERIALL, AND THIRTY ROY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALL <hi>HEAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SPRINGS:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HIS ESSAYES, LATINE AND ENGLISH, DONE AND TO BEE DONE, IN HONOVR OF OVR MOST GRATIOVS KING &amp; QVEENE AND OF THEIR MOST HOPEFVL CHILDREN, HVMBLY DEDICATETH]</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IAMES MAXWEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO THE COVRTEOVS READER, TOVCHING THE REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of this preſent Dedication to the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Houſe of</hi> HOVVARDS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Muſe, courteous Reader, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing meditated certaine Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall and Poeticall Eſſayes, as well in Latine, as in Engliſh, in honour of our moſt gracious King <hi>Iames,</hi> his moſt Noble wife Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> and of their moſt hopefull children, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> her Spouſe, in whoſe common extraction &amp; deſcent, I haue remarked no fewer then 25. Emperours, and 30. Kings of diuers Countries, I reſolued with my ſelfe to commend the ſame to the honourable Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of the Illuſtrious houſe of <hi>Howard,</hi> for theſe reaſons following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe of the ſingular excellencie of this name, in whoſe extraction no fewer then 12. Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and 30. Kings of diuers Countries, are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereof moſt part are the ſame Emperours and Kings which do occurre in the extraction common
<pb facs="tcp:12855:7"/>to the aboue-named, two moſt Noble Princes, as ſhall bee ſhewed, God-willing, in our Latine worke: and truely it muſt needs be a thing that doth much il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate and commend, the exceellencie and honour of our King and Country, to haue ſuch Subiects as this worthy houſe doth yeeld, being ſo Nobilitated by the meanes both of their Princely deſcent, and of their publicke deſerts, as they are.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe of a certaine kind of honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and notable ſimilitude, and affinity, that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble name of <hi>Howard</hi> hath with the Royall name of <hi>Steward;</hi> for both names do ſignifie, in the old Saxon tongue, as much as the Warden, or Gouernour of a a Place, Fort, or Caſtle; both being at the firſt impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by reaſon of the charge, preferment and place, the two firſt perſones, that were ſo named, did beare in the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>So that theſe two Sur-names, may truely ſay, that which many other Sur-names cannot ſay; which is, that the firſt two Wights, that euer bare the names of <hi>Steward</hi> and <hi>Howard,</hi> as they were both borne in South-britanny, ſo were they both men of quality, reputation and rancke, and euen ſuch, as wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly name Gentlemen, and Noblemen.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, as both names giue the Lyon Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, though different in coulour, for their badge or Armes; ſo both can fetch their Pedigree from diuers of the ſame Emperours, and Kings of diuers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and namely from Kings of England, and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Likewiſe both names haue beene matched with the Royall bloud of England; for as <hi>Margaret,</hi> a daughter of England, was married to a Royall
<pb facs="tcp:12855:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Steward</hi> of Scotland, King <hi>Iames</hi> the 4. (in the which buſineſſe a Noble <hi>Howard</hi> had an eſpeciall employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſo <hi>Katherine,</hi> a daughter of the houſe of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> was married to a King of England, <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. Beſides, that famous Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from this Illuſtrious houſe on her mothers ſide, the Lady <hi>Anne Bolen,</hi> whoſe mother was the Lady <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth Howard</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Wilſhire</hi> and <hi>Ormond,</hi> daughter to <hi>Thomas,</hi> the firſt of this name, Duke of <hi>Norfolke.</hi> As alſo the foreſaid two Names, haue had the fortune to ſeeke and aime at a three-fold matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Vnion one with another. The firſt attempt and deſigne of marriage (but hindered) was betweene a Royall <hi>Steward,</hi> euen a matchleſſe Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and a Princely <hi>Howard, Thomas</hi> the third of this name, Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> brother to <hi>Henry,</hi> Earle of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton,</hi> Lord Priuy-ſeale, father to <hi>Thomas,</hi> Earle of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine, &amp; Grand-father to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell,</hi> the ſonne of Earle <hi>Phillip.</hi> The ſecond attempt, or deſigne of marriage, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſonne and daughter of the fore-ſaid two Princes, to wit, betweene <hi>Charles-Iames <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ward</hi> Prince of Scotland, and the Lady <hi>Margaret Howard,</hi> which was likewiſe hindred with the former. The third deſigne onely tooke effect, by the vniting-meanes of our Concording-King, the Maker of the marriage betweene <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> Earle of <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> Lord <hi>Admirall,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Margaret Steward</hi> daughter of <hi>Iames</hi> Earle of <hi>Murrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it hath bene the common fortune of both theſe names to reape much good lucke, and preferment, either of them by the meanes of three
<pb facs="tcp:12855:8"/>Ladies, being both of the ſame Country, and of the ſame names, to wit, either of them by two <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> and one <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> The three Engliſh Ladies, which brought good fortune to the Royall name of <hi>Steward,</hi> were theſe; firſt, <hi>Margaret,</hi> the daughter of Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> ſur-named the <hi>Out-law,</hi> ſon of King <hi>Edmond Ironſide,</hi> who being married to <hi>Malcolme Cammore</hi> King of Scotland, brought to King <hi>Iames,</hi> the firſt right of ſucceſſion to this Crowne; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Yorke,</hi> daughter to King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. married to King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. of the houſe of <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Margaret,</hi> their eldeſt daughter borne in the bleſſed white-red Vnion-bed of the two Roſes, who being married to <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth, king of Scotland, brought the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond right of ſucceſſion to our moſt gracious King <hi>Iames,</hi> the happy Vniter of the two Kingdomes. To theſe three Ladies of <hi>Britanny,</hi> wee may adde other theſe of <hi>Germany,</hi> bearing the ſame names, from the which King <hi>Iames,</hi> and his hopefull children, namely, Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> are collineally deſcended, and they are theſe; firſt, <hi>Margaret</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Holland,</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Bauier</hi> and Empreſſe, wife to <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the 5. Duke of <hi>Bauier</hi> and Emperour; ſecondly, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Princeſſe <hi>Palatine</hi> &amp; Empreſſe, wife to <hi>Robert</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> and Emperour, thirdly, <hi>Margaret</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> their daughter. And it is my ardent wiſh that the fore-ſaid two <hi>Germane Margarets</hi> and <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> may proue as lucky to King <hi>Iames,</hi> and his hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children for their Imperiall preferment in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> as the two Engliſh <hi>Margarets</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> haue done for his Royall preferment in <hi>Britanny.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And the three Ladies of the ſame names which brought good fortune and preferment to the houſe of <hi>Howard,</hi> were theſe; firſt, <hi>Margaret Plantagenet</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> the onely daughter and heire of <hi>Thomas Plantagenet,</hi> Earle of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> ſon to King <hi>Edward</hi> the 1: ſecondly, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Lady <hi>Segraue,</hi> the daughter and heire of the ſaid Lady-Dutcheſſe <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Segrane;</hi> thirdly, <hi>Margaret Mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray,</hi> daughter of the ſaid Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and of <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Mowbray,</hi> maried to Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi> Knight, the father and mother of <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke.</hi> So that as a <hi>Robert</hi> was the firſt Royall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitor of the Royall <hi>Stewards,</hi> King <hi>Robert</hi> the <hi>Bruce</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Noble,</hi> being the Grand-father of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> the firſt King of the <hi>Stewards;</hi> and as a <hi>Robert</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> and Emperour, likewiſe ſur-named the <hi>Noble,</hi> is he, from whom King <hi>Iames</hi> and Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> are deſcended both in the 9. degree (as our late publiſhed Pedigree doth ſhow) ſo was a Noble <hi>Robert</hi> the firſt Progenitor of the Dukes of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> of the honoured name of <hi>Howard,</hi> vnto whoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Patronage, wee thought good, for the reaſons afore-ſaid, and others wee might mention, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our Eſſayes in Latine and Engliſh (whereof theſe Preſents are but a ſcantling) vndertaken by vs, in honour of a number of moſt Noble Princes: And thus, Courteous Reader, crauing thy fauourable conſtruction of theſe our endeuours, wee hauing no other intent, but onely thereby to do honour in a ſchollar-like kind, to ſuch as are worthy of honour, we bid thee hartely fare-well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ALBIONS Remembrance of <hi>FREDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RICKE</hi> and <hi>ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ITH Norths bright Nymph, and <hi>Albions</hi> Roſie</l>
               <l>The ſweeteſt, meekeſt of the Lady-kind</l>
               <l>Muſt bound from vs to build her Summers bowre Flowre</l>
               <l>At <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> now in this flowry time;</l>
               <l>And that for <hi>Rhine,</hi> ſhe muſt abandon <hi>Thames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Germany</hi> leauing the land of IAMES:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>And ſith Her preſence ſweete we muſt no more</l>
               <l>Injoy, (alas) which was the ioy of hearts</l>
               <l>To all Her ſex, as HENRIES was before</l>
               <l>To thoſe of His, men, women of all parts;</l>
               <l>Which came to Court, to veiw the worth, and State</l>
               <l>Which their did ſhine through Him and Her of late:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Sith that, I ſay, now <hi>Hymen</hi> doth her call</l>
               <l>From th'Ile of IEMMES to dwell in <hi>Germaines</hi> ground;</l>
               <l>So that her face no more hence ſee wee ſhall,</l>
               <l>Her face, the grace of Country, Court and Towne;</l>
               <l>What reſts? but that we wiſh her aſmuch ioy</l>
               <l>As by her abſence we muſt reape annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:10"/>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>For like as did deere <hi>Henry</hi> by his death</l>
               <l>Make men to mourne, but mirth to Angels bring;</l>
               <l>So the departure of <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Make <hi>Britans</hi> ſigh, but <hi>Germaines</hi> for to ſing:</l>
               <l>Thus in one yeare, we drinke of double woes,</l>
               <l>By looſing firſt our Lilly, then our Roſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Which double loſſe might well our Iland drowne</l>
               <l>In ſorrowes ſea, except there did remaine</l>
               <l>A Lilly-Roſe with ioy our land to crowne,</l>
               <l>To ſalue the ſorrowes which wee do ſuſtaine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry, Eliza:</hi> both their flowers bequeath,</l>
               <l>To make for <hi>Charles</hi> a Lilly-roſie wreath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux</hi> of all bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that haue bene were the moſt louingſt, as <hi>Aratus, Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodorus</hi> &amp; <hi>Hygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> do write, &amp; euen ſo louing, that the one would needs halue with the other his immortall State. <hi>Plutarch</hi> doth likewiſe tell how that <hi>Cleomenes</hi> of <hi>Lacedemonia</hi> did loue his brother <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clides</hi> ſo deerely, that he made him his coequall in the Kingdome: and in our time or memory, there was neuer one that loued his brother more deerely then our peereleſſe Prince <hi>Henry</hi> did his brother Duke <hi>Charles.</hi>
                  </note>For like as <hi>Pollux</hi> to his brother deere</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſtor</hi> by name, his glory did impart;</l>
               <l>Haluing with him his owne Immortall Sphere,</l>
               <l>So much had <hi>Caſtor</hi> of Prince <hi>Pollux</hi> heart:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo would <hi>Henry</hi> halue his Princely State,</l>
               <l>That his lou'd <hi>Charles</hi> might it participate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7</head>
               <l>Me thinkes I ſee ſweete HENRY with his hand</l>
               <l>Plucking the choiſeſt flowers of Paradiſe;</l>
               <l>One day to decke this twiſe defloured Land</l>
               <l>With <hi>Syons</hi> ſtore, to make it happy thriſe;</l>
               <l>Euen now he makes a Garland for the day,</l>
               <l>That CHARLES ſhall beare <hi>Conſtantixes</hi> crowne away.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:10"/>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8</head>
               <l>Likewiſe <hi>Eliza</hi> goes to breed and bring</l>
               <l>Forth to the light, ſonnes of a noble kinde,</l>
               <l>Whoſe worth one day, ſhall make vs <hi>Britans</hi> ſing,</l>
               <l>When they with CHARLES vnanimely combin'd</l>
               <l>(<note n="*" place="margin">This ſhall be ſhewed in our <hi>Sybilla Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</hi> containing Propheſies in ſiue ſundry Languages, which ſeeme to promiſe no leſſe.</note> As is fore-rold) in ſpight of Turkiſh might</l>
               <l>Shall once regaine great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gonilda</hi> the faire, daughter of <hi>Canute</hi> the <hi>Daniſh</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, &amp; <hi>Mathil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> or <hi>Maud,</hi> the daughter and heire of <hi>Henry</hi> the 1. K. of <hi>England,</hi> maried to <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. Emperour; reade hereof <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmeſbury,</hi> and <hi>Roger Houeden</hi> their Hiſtories.</note>A better hap, we hope this Match ſhall haue,</l>
               <l>Then once two <hi>Engliſh-Germaine</hi> Matches had,</l>
               <l>That to their Countries did no Iſſue leaue;</l>
               <l>Which made <hi>Gonilda</hi> and <hi>Mathilda</hi> ſad:</l>
               <l>Kings daughters both, the ſecond <hi>Englands</hi> Dame,</l>
               <l>To Emperours matcht, both HENRIES by their name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10</head>
               <l>And better then had once that match in <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Twixt <hi>Francis</hi> and our <hi>Scotlands</hi> noble Queene,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Mary</hi> hight; and yet a better chance</l>
               <l>Then of that Match for to enſue was ſeene</l>
               <l>Twixt <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> when Queene <hi>Mary</hi> thought</l>
               <l>With <hi>Phillip</hi> a great Vnion to haue wrought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Robert</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Prince <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> &amp; Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, had by his wife <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly children, fiue ſons &amp; three daughters, whereof reade in <hi>Cuſtinianus, Munſteru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> &amp; <hi>Reuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus:</hi> and from them two, Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>dericke</hi> and Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are both lineally deſcended, hee in the ninth, and ſhee in the tenth degree, as may be ſeene in the Pede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree I haue lately publiſhed) the which numbers in them vnited make vp King IAMES his auſpicious &amp; lucky number of Nineteene, which is likewiſe the number of the coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Lyon, according to <hi>Hyginus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Germanicus Caeſar</hi> writing vpon <hi>Aratus;</hi> as alſo of the Kingdomes &amp; Prince-domes into which the Ile of <hi>Britanny,</hi> with <hi>Ireland,</hi> in former ages, haue bene deuided; the which are now all happely vnited in One, in the perſon of the Lilly-Lyon of the North, and in this vnited State long may they continue, aye vntill all the Kingdomes of the earth bee fully vnited in the glorious perſon of the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> who delighteth to feede among the Lillies; as it is in the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
                  </note>The heauens <hi>Eliza</hi> will with Iſſue bleſſe</l>
               <l>By <hi>Fredericke</hi> her Spouſe from <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſprung,</l>
               <l>Such is our hope, and ſuch ſhall be our wiſh,</l>
               <l>That ſongs may be of their ſweete Iſſue ſung;</l>
               <l>When as it ſhall befall them as it hath</l>
               <l>Before to * <hi>Robert</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:11"/>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The two <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Kings of <hi>England</hi> the 1. and the 2. had either of them a daughter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Mathilde</hi> or <hi>Maud,</hi> and both of them were married to two <hi>Henries</hi> of <hi>Germany:</hi> the firſt King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Mathilde</hi> was his onely daughter and heire, and was wedded at fiue yeeres old to <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. Emperour, and was crowned Empreſſe at <hi>Mentz,</hi> on Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his day, in the yeere 1114. being of the age as ſaid is of 5. who after the deceaſe of her husband, dying without iſſue, <hi>annó</hi> 1116. returned to her father King <hi>Henry,</hi> bringing with her the Imperiall Crowne, and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his hand, in honour whereof hee founded the Abbey and Church of S. <hi>Mary</hi> in <hi>Reading,</hi> as <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmſbury, William</hi> of <hi>Gemite, Roger Houedon,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Walſingham</hi> doe write. The which deed of this North-South deſcended Lady (for her father was King of <hi>England,</hi> and her mother another renowned <hi>Mathildis</hi> was a daughter of <hi>Scotland</hi> borne of S. <hi>Margaret,</hi> and King <hi>Malcolme</hi>) me thinkes did beare this good ſignification; that once a <hi>Iames,</hi> and he the ſon of a Matchleſſe <hi>Mary,</hi> both of them hauing in their perſons vnited the Royall blouds of both Countries, ſhould euen at the feaſt of the Annunciation of the glorious Virgin MARY, enter to the vniting of theſe Kingdomes, and that he ſhould at the Feaſt of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> receiue the Imperiall Crowne of the ſame vnited Kingdomes on his happy head: Whereof there is more to be read in our Poem, that ſheweth both by Theology &amp; Aſtrology the auſpiciouſneſſe of his Maieſties entry to this Crowne; for whereas there haue bene three diuers deſignes attempted before at three diuers times, to vnite this Iland with three diuers Nations, <hi>Germany, France,</hi> &amp; &amp; <hi>Spaine,</hi> by the meanes of the Marriages of three Queene-heires, <hi>Maud</hi> and the two <hi>Maries,</hi> it was the great Vnion-Makers will to make the fore-ſaid three Matches all fruitleſſe, to the end that it might be firſt fully and perfitely vnited with, and in it owne ſelfe, before any other ſuch Vnion with any forraine Nation ſhould be made, as by thoſe three marriages was intended and expected; and when I compare the deſignes &amp; deeds of the three <hi>Maries</hi> together; firſt of <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by her Mariage with King <hi>Phillip,</hi> labouring to vnite this Iland in whole, or in part with <hi>Spaine;</hi> next of <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Lorvaine</hi> by the Mariage of her yong daughter <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> with <hi>Francis</hi> the Dolphin, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to vnite it with <hi>France,</hi> and laſtly of the ſame <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by her ſecond Marriage with her deereſt couſen, <hi>Henry,</hi> Lord <hi>Darly,</hi> Earle of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Albuny,</hi> great-grand-child of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. intending to vnite this Iland with it ſelfe, in her happy Iſſue, when as I compare together, I ſay, the fore-ſaid three diuers deſignes and endeuours of the fore-ſaid three <hi>Maries,</hi> I am conſtrained to giue out this verdite and cenſure concerning the ſame; that the firſt two <hi>Maries</hi> were with <hi>Martha</hi> in the Goſpell combred about many things, but that the third <hi>Mary,</hi> with <hi>Mary</hi> in the ſame Goſpell, <hi>had choſen the better part, which was not to be taken from her.</hi>
                     <p>The other <hi>Mathildis</hi> or <hi>Maude,</hi> married into <hi>Germany,</hi> was the daughter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, wedded to <hi>Henry</hi> ſurnamed the Lyon, Duke of <hi>Bauier</hi> and <hi>Saxe,</hi> and bare him diuers children, namely <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxe,</hi> &amp;c. and Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> in right of his wife <hi>Agnes,</hi> heire of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> by meanes whereof Prince <hi>Fredricke</hi> is deſcended from the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. in the 17. degree. Another of their ſaid children was <hi>Otho</hi> Lord of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Yorke,</hi> created by his vnckle King <hi>Richard,</hi> ſur-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Lyons-heart, who alſo was choſen Emperour afterwards, and from him Prince <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> is both on his fathers and his mothers ſide deſcended, in the 13. and 14 degrees, though ſome haue written, that he left no Iſſue by any of his wiues. He is much wronged by Hiſtorians, for that he was an enemy to the Popes vſurped ſuper-Imperiall power, and his. Temporall vſurpations; for when as hee did feaſt Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the 3. in <hi>Rome,</hi> being then his friend, it chanced that hee made a motion to haue ſome things reſtored to the Empire, which the Pope did poſſeſſe, where-with he was ſo highly offended, that he preſumptuouſly took vp a ſword to haue ſtricken the Emperor, and afterwards did both Excommunicate him, and pronounce the ſentence of depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt him, whom before hee had aduanced to that dignity: reade <hi>Vrſpergenſis, Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinianus, Carion, Pedro de Mexia,</hi> and others.</p>
                  </note>Heauens her vouch ſafe both the <hi>Mathilda's</hi> fate</l>
               <l>Two <hi>Henries</hi> girles both of South-britanny,</l>
               <l>Betroth'd to <hi>Henries,</hi> two of greateſt ſtate</l>
               <l>They <hi>Germaines</hi> both; that <hi>Britanes</hi> once may ſee,</l>
               <l>When with the firſt <hi>Mathilde Eliza</hi> ſhall</l>
               <l>Weare on her head the wreath Imperiall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>13</head>
               <l>And as the next <hi>Mathilda</hi> oft was ſeene</l>
               <l>To bleſſe her Spouſe with plenteous Progeny.</l>
               <l>Both with a <hi>Caeſar</hi> and a <hi>Palatine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To rule in <hi>Brunſwicke, Rhine,</hi> and <hi>Saxony:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So may <hi>Eliza</hi> with <hi>Mathilda</hi> beare</l>
               <l>Vnto her Spouſe a <hi>Caeſar</hi> and a Peere.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:11"/>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iagello</hi> great Duke of <hi>Lithu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any</hi> married <hi>Hedwigis</hi> heire of <hi>Poland,</hi> &amp; daughter of <hi>Lodowick</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi>
                  </note>And like as once the braue <hi>Hungarian</hi> Heire,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did crowne her <hi>Caſimire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great <hi>Polands</hi> King, when as ſhee to him bare</l>
               <l>Sixe ſonnes, beſides as many daughters deere;</l>
               <l>So may to our <hi>Elizabeth</hi> befull,</l>
               <l>Like fruitefull fate to crowne her Spouſe withall.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:12"/>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>15</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Poland,</hi> on S. <hi>Valentines</hi> day; and his ſonne <hi>Caſimire</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about the ſame time <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebeth</hi> heire of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Albert</hi> the 2. Emperour, Arch-duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and King of <hi>Boheme</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> by whom he had ſixe ſonnes, whereof foure were Kings of <hi>Poland, Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Boheme,</hi> and as many daughters.</note>That euen as hee from <hi>Caſimire</hi> doth ſpring,</l>
               <l>And from his wife twiſe Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So his <hi>Elizabeth</hi> may make him ſing,</l>
               <l>When he by her ſuch hopefull children hath;</l>
               <l>Like hap to both, ſith both had hap to marry,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza's</hi> two about mid-February.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> who did his ſweeteſt ſiſter loue</l>
               <l>With heart ſo pure, ſo ſure, me thinkes I ſee</l>
               <l>How he doth beg leaue of the Powers aboue</l>
               <l>For to come downe from heauen to <hi>Germany:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bringing with him a Garland for the day,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Heidelberge</hi> ſalutes her Queene of May.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abrahams</hi> hill in Dutch, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Abrinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge,</hi> is a hill on the right hand of <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge,</hi> and is in the ancient Records of that Citty called S. <hi>Abrahami Mons,</hi> as <hi>Irenicus, Leodius,</hi> and <hi>Marquardus</hi> do witneſſe.</note>Me thinkes I ſee him, from Saint <hi>Abrahams</hi> hill</l>
               <l>By <hi>Heidelberge</hi> inſpiring euery wight,</l>
               <l>How to vnite their Powers, wit and skill,</l>
               <l>Their Towne to decke with greateſt glory bright,</l>
               <l>Againſt the day that his deere Siſter ſweete,</l>
               <l>In greateſt ſtate muſt ride along the ſtreete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>18</head>
               <l>But firſt I ſee him from his owne Saint <hi>Iames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Inſpiring all the Worthies of this Iſle</l>
               <l>With greateſt ſtate to bring her to the Thames,</l>
               <l>In ſuch array, that twiſe ten thouſand mile</l>
               <l>Both tongues and Tribes may talke of that daies glory,</l>
               <l>When ſhe departs; and put it in ſome Story.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:12"/>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>19</head>
               <l>Come Nobles all, come Worthies, Beauties bright</l>
               <l>With your beſt things adorne <hi>Eliza's</hi> day,</l>
               <l>Flocke from all parts, and grace you with her ſight,</l>
               <l>Before that ſhe, ſweete one, be gone her way;</l>
               <l>Let euery wight that any honour hath</l>
               <l>Come honour all-belou'd <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>20</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmeſ berry</hi> and <hi>Mathew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in their Hiſtories do make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence was vſed of the Nobility of <hi>England</hi> in conueying of <hi>Gonilda</hi> the faire daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> King of <hi>England Canute</hi> to her ſhip; it was ſo great, that they exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted their whole treaſure for coſtly apparell to themſelues, and pretious preſents to the Bride at her departure: The Muſitians and Minſtrels, at feaſts and banquets, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies wont to celebrate the ſtately and Princely pompe thereof in their ſongs, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that they could neuer ſufficiently magnifie and extoll the ſame.</note>Let not the glory of <hi>Gouilda's</hi> day</l>
               <l>So much extol'd in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>When as ſhe did from <hi>England</hi> take her way</l>
               <l>To her Spouſe <hi>Henry</hi> into <hi>Germany:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let not her day <hi>Elizaes</hi> day ſurpaſſe,</l>
               <l>Sith ſhe's as good, as e're <hi>Gonilda</hi> was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>21</head>
               <l>Flocke men and women from the fartheſt parts</l>
               <l>To view <hi>Elizaes</hi> face, her grace, her glory;</l>
               <l>Come and adore this worthy Queene of hearts,</l>
               <l>And hauing ſeene her keepe in memory</l>
               <l>What once yee ſaw, who ne're ſhall liue the howre,</l>
               <l>To ſee tranſ-planted ſuch a gallant Flowre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22</head>
               <l>Yee tender Virgins come before her face,</l>
               <l>Her face wherein all manner-worth doth ſhine,</l>
               <l>And with a ſong ſee yee ſalute her Grace,</l>
               <l>Lauding <hi>Eliza</hi> with her <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wiſhing that them as many daies may crowne,</l>
               <l>As there grows Vines vpon the <hi>Rheniſh</hi> ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:13"/>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>23</head>
               <l>And yee bright ſtarres extend your influenter.</l>
               <l>And for her ſake, ſo yee the Seaſon frame</l>
               <l>That it obſcure not her magnificence,</l>
               <l>But rather adde ſome luſter to the ſame:</l>
               <l>Thou golden <hi>Phoebus</hi> bind thy brighteſt raies</l>
               <l>To laſt as long, as ſhall her progreſſe daies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>24</head>
               <l>That as the skies her nuptiall rites did grace,</l>
               <l>With ſweeteſt ſmiles after a ſtor my time</l>
               <l>Of boiſterous blaſts, ſo euery time and place,</l>
               <l>Both heauen and earth their bounties may combine,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Flora</hi> and her Nymphes of greateſt ſtate</l>
               <l>Belou'd <hi>Eliza</hi> to congratulate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>25</head>
               <l>But if our heauens will needs ſome ſorrow ſhow,</l>
               <l>And ſhed ſome teares when as ſhe doth depart,</l>
               <l>And weepe with vs, as grieuing to forgoe</l>
               <l>So ſweete a wight, that cheer'd each eie and heart:</l>
               <l>Yet muſt heauens weeping end, when ſhe ſhall riſe</l>
               <l>Her cleeren eſſe bene enough to cleere the skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26</head>
               <l>A Seaſon ſweete, to ſweete <hi>Elizaes</hi> due,</l>
               <l>A Beamy time befits ſo braue a Wight,</l>
               <l>Freſh <hi>Flora</hi> flaunting in her gariſh hue</l>
               <l>And Violet weed, muſt tend her day and night,</l>
               <l>With all her traine, till they <hi>Eliza</hi> crowne,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heidelberge</hi> by interpretation is as much as a Hill or Towne of Myrtles, from the which it takes the name, according to the opinion of <hi>Franciſcus Irenicus, Michael Bohemus,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Meliſſus,</hi> becauſe of the great aboundance of Myrtle, berries which grow thereabout, they are called here in <hi>England</hi> Whirtle-berries, and in <hi>Scotland</hi> Blea-berries.</note>With Myrtle-wreath, amids the * <hi>Myrtle-towne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:13"/>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>27</head>
               <l>The <hi>Argoſie</hi> wherein Prince <hi>Iaſon</hi> went</l>
               <l>To <hi>Colehos</hi> ground to fetch the golden Fleece,</l>
               <l>Once ſtellified amids the firmament,</l>
               <l>After that it had long decored <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This ſhip turn'd ſtarre, e'ne <note n="*" place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellarion cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Argo,</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Iaſons</hi> ſhip, conſiſteth of many ſtars, wherof 18. are of the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, &amp; third magnitudes; it doth riſein the Spring ſeaſon according to the obſeruation of Aſtronomers; the 13. of March after <hi>Ptolomies</hi> Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but ſomewhat ſooner according to the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> of the <hi>Modernes,</hi> and ſomewhat later according to the ancient Kalender of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> which placeth the riſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vpon the fifth of Aprill: See <hi>Prolomeus, Aratus, Hyginus, Picolominaeus, Maginus, Stadius,</hi> and others.</note> now ſhe doth ariſe</l>
               <l>To calme the ſeas, and for to cleere the skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>28</head>
               <l>When I behold the twinkling of her face,</l>
               <l>Shee lookes as if ſhee had a deepe deſire</l>
               <l>To leaue a while her high aethereall place</l>
               <l>Which ſhe now holds amongſt thoſe flames of fire,</l>
               <l>For to deſcend amids our Riuer Thames,</l>
               <l>Thence to tranſport the golden Fleece of IAMES.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29</head>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſtor</hi> &amp; <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux</hi> were borne the ſeuenth of Aprill, and on the ſame day antiently their birth was cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of them, for that they did ſcoure the ſeas from Pirates and Rouers, ſo that after their death they were held of Mariners and Sailers for their Patrons and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors from the danger of Pyrates: See the ancient Pontificall Kalender, <hi>Arotus, Hygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and others.</note>
                  <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> which therein did ſaile,</l>
               <l>Borne in Aprill to baniſh Piracie</l>
               <l>Bid their ſtar'd ſhip take downe herflags and vaile</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Prince-Henry</hi> of great <hi>Britanny;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You ſhip (ſay they) it beares a better Fleece,</l>
               <l>Then that which once our <hi>Arge</hi> fetcht to <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:14"/>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>30</head>
               <l>The Virgin-ſigne <note n="*" place="margin">Of <hi>Eliza's</hi> natruity in the ſigne of <hi>Virgo;</hi> ſee more in our Poem made vpon that ſubiect; &amp; in a goodtime, two of the ſaid <hi>Virgo's</hi> brighteſt ſtarres, the one called <hi>Spica Virginis</hi> of the firſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, the other called <hi>Cingulum Virginis</hi> of the third magnitude, do ariſe at night, the one the ſeuenth, the other the eighth of Aprill, as it were for <hi>Elizaes</hi> ſake, to light her all the nights of her voiage, chiefly vpon the ſea: See <hi>Hyginus, Maginus, Picolominaeus.</hi>
                  </note> which did <hi>Eliza</hi> beare</l>
               <l>Bids faſt ariſe two of her greateſt lights,</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Zona-ſtarre,</hi> and then her <hi>Spica</hi> cleere</l>
               <l>To chaſe all Langour from ſo many nights,</l>
               <l>As her deere daughter in her Ship muſt ſtay,</l>
               <l>And for her ſake ſhe turnes the night to day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>31</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tethis</hi> commands her daughter <hi>Doris</hi> then</l>
               <l>Her wonted bitterneſſe to ſet aſide,</l>
               <l>For feare to be rebuk'd of Gods and men,</l>
               <l>If any frownes ſhould in her face be ſpi'd:</l>
               <l>Sith heauen and earth (ſaith ſhe) do ſmile to day;</l>
               <l>It's meete that we put bitterneſſe away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>32</head>
               <l>The louing <note n="*" place="margin">Sixe famous Hiſtorians <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Pauſanias, Plutarchus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenaeus, Elia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Solinus</hi> doe relate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, of the affection of the Dolphins towards Mankind, and of their forewardneſſe to reſcue them from dangers on the ſea: It is the ſwifteſt of all creatures by land or ſea, ſwifter then an arrow, or a ſwallow, it hath no gall, it delighteth in Muſicke, and loues to be called <hi>Simon,</hi> it is alwaies in motion, both ſleeping and waking, and ſo is the tongue of it moueable, contrary to the nature of Sea-creatures, it will eate out of a mans hand; it loues to leape and play about ſhips on the ſea, it fore-ſmelleth Tempeſts and ſtormes before they fall, they haue borne little boies on their backes from ſhore to ſhore, they haue reſcued many from the danger of drowning in the ſea, they haue brought the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the dead in the ſea to the ſhore; they haue proued many waies thankefull to ſuch as haue deliuered them from the hands of Fiſhers, as they did to <hi>Caeranus</hi> the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiane</hi> whom they deliuered from ſhipwracke when all his fellowes did drowne, and when his funerall-fire was in making, neere to the ſea-ſide of <hi>Miletus</hi> they were ſeene in the neereſt they could come to the ſhore, to ſolemnize in their manner <hi>Coeranus</hi> their redeemers obſequies. There is ſuch a kind of brotherly loue amongſt them, that when any one of them chanceth to bee taken, they do in great troupes repaire before the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, making ſignes of entreaty for their fellowes releaſe. <hi>Aelianus</hi> doth write that there is, in diuers reſpects, a great ſimilitude and reſemblance betweene the Lyon, the King of land-beaſts, and the Dolphin the King of ſea-creatures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Finally, the Ancients had the Dolphins in ſo great veneration, for their admirable Mankind-nature, that they eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it a thing vnlawfull to take them, or to do them any harme; and therefore <hi>Oppianus</hi> exclaimeth againſt the <hi>Bizantins</hi> for their vnkind killing &amp; eating of ſo kind a creature: the which thing learned <hi>Caſaubonus</hi> hath likewiſe obſerued in his Commentaries vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n <hi>Athenaeus.</hi>
                  </note> Dolphins they do flocke apace,</l>
               <l>From fartheſt coaſts her <hi>Argoe</hi> to attend;</l>
               <l>And that they may their fill behold her face</l>
               <l>Aboue the Maſts they often bound and bend,</l>
               <l>Waiting if any dangerous ſtorme ſhould be,</l>
               <l>Them to reſcue from ſhip-wrackes ieopardy.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:14"/>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>33</head>
               <l>As once they did that louing <note n="*" place="margin">The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Smin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> loued by <hi>Aenalus</hi> as is in <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lesbian</hi> Laſſe</l>
               <l>With her deere Lad turn'd o're into the ſeas</l>
               <l>Bring ſafe to ſhore, when greateſt danger was,</l>
               <l>And that ſowre death with ſpeed began to ſeaſe</l>
               <l>On their ſweete foules, which quite had drowned bene;</l>
               <l>If that <hi>Ioues</hi> Dolphins had not bene their friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arion</hi> the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition his reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuage by a Dolphin is ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated by the common teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, and both <hi>Herodotus</hi> &amp; <hi>Hyginus</hi> do write, how that <hi>Pyranthus</hi> or <hi>Periander</hi> King of <hi>Corinth,</hi> who loued <hi>Arion</hi> for his melodie and skill of Muſick, did reare vp a ſtately monument &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in honour of that Dolphin that reſcued him, and made hang the mercileſſe Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which had intended his death, before the ſaid Monument. Finally, <hi>Steſichorus</hi> and <hi>Plutarchus</hi> do report, how that <hi>Telemachus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> being ſaued by a Dolphin from drowning, his father in remembrance therof euer bare thereafter the picture of a Dolphin in his Shield, Signet, and Sword pomell.</note>So did they once ſweete-an'd <hi>Arion</hi> ſaue</l>
               <l>Amids the waues from Sailers hurtfull hand:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Telemachus</hi> nie drown'd they did not leaue,</l>
               <l>But him reſcu'd, and fet him on the land:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spartane</hi> Captaine <hi>Phalant</hi> they did free</l>
               <l>From mournefull ſhipwrackes preſent miſery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>35</head>
               <l>Now if the Mankind Dolphins had ſuch care</l>
               <l>To ſhield and ſaue the perſons nam'd before,</l>
               <l>With many others which recorded are</l>
               <l>In Hiſtories; would they not yet much more</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tamiſis</hi> Nymph reſcue from danger neere,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Grandame was a <hi>Dolphins</hi> deereſt deere.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:15"/>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>36</head>
               <l>No ſooner <hi>Neptune</hi> gets her in his bounds,</l>
               <l>But with his Trident, he doth calme the ſeas,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tethis</hi> his Queene her welcomes to their grounds,</l>
               <l>And in glad wiſe giues order for her eaſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeol</hi> doth that, he neuer did before,</l>
               <l>With muſky breath hee blowes her to the ſhore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37</head>
               <l>So ſoone as <hi>Rhine</hi> receiues her Roſie ſmell,</l>
               <l>That pure chaſt floud, wherein <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſtathius</hi> vpon the <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy</hi> of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius, Iulianus</hi> the Emperour in his Epiſtle to <hi>Maximus</hi> the Philoſopher, and <hi>Politianus</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Iacobus Cardinalis Papienſis,</hi> with others more, doc make mention of the Riuer of <hi>Rhines</hi> admirable nature, in iudging of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke-breach, for if yong children bee ſet on the ſaid water, if they haue beene wel-gotten, it beareth them vp, and, as it were, ſendeth them backe againe with her appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation to their honeſt mothers; where as ſuch as haue beene begotten with any ſpot or blot, comming by falſe play, ſhee ouerwhelmeth them, or rather ſwalloweth them vp in the midſt of her pooles; ſhewing thereby, that ſhe would be auenged in the ſame manner vpon their polluted mothers if they were in their place.</note> ſtrange iudgement lies,</l>
               <l>And finds how much ſhe doth in worth excell;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rhine</hi> doth reioyce, and her ſalutes this wiſe:</l>
               <l>Welcome pure Nymph, moſt worthy to be Queene,</l>
               <l>Of all the ſhamefaſt faces I haue ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <head>38</head>
               <l>Stately <hi>Tam-Iſis</hi> might of thee be proud,</l>
               <l>That art another <hi>Iſis</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">That <hi>Gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> and <hi>Scota</hi> were of the <hi>Argiuian</hi> &amp; <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> bloud of <hi>Oſiris</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſis,</hi> and that they were the true Progenitors of the moſt part of our Ilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, it ſhall bee ſhewed in our booke of <hi>Britanniſh anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Strabo, Beroſus, Diodorus, Plutarchus, Plinius,</hi> &amp; others, <hi>Iſis</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Argiues,</hi> and the wife of <hi>Oſiris</hi> her owne brothers ſonne; for <hi>Phoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> King of <hi>Argiues</hi> was his father, who was the ſonne of <hi>Inachus.</hi> They reigned firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Argiues,</hi> and then amongſt the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> whom they taught ciuility, Arts and Sciences, of whom they were honored as their King and Queene during their life, and after their death as their Patrons and Gods, becauſe of the great happineſſe which they enioyed by the meanes of their gouernment ſo long as they liued.</note> her child,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Scota</hi> was of honoured <hi>Iſis</hi> brood;</l>
               <l>So was <hi>Gathele</hi> once famous in your Ile;</l>
               <l>But looke how deere thou waſt to <hi>Thames</hi> before,</l>
               <l>As deere to <hi>Rhine</hi> thou art, and ſhall be more.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:15"/>
            <lg n="39">
               <head>39</head>
               <l>In ſigne whereof I ſweare by <hi>Tethys</hi> Queene,</l>
               <l>I'le welcome thee with greateſt cheere I can;</l>
               <l>For on thy day a wonder ſhall be ſeene,</l>
               <l>Which neuer yet was ſeene of any man.</l>
               <l>No wonted water ſhall be ſeene in <hi>Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For all my ſtreames ſhall taſte of <hi>Rheniſh wine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40</head>
               <l>All day the <hi>Dolphins</hi> ſhall bee ſeene to dance,</l>
               <l>And cut their capers on my floting flore,</l>
               <l>Freſh <hi>Tethys</hi> Girles ſhall think't a happy chance,</l>
               <l>If they that day may faile along my ſhore</l>
               <l>To view the Face, the Grace and Maieſty</l>
               <l>Of faire <hi>Tamiſis</hi> Nymph of <hi>Britanny.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41</head>
               <l>The Palſgraues ground, the firſt that ſhe ſhall touch</l>
               <l>At her arriuall, ſhall be gaily ſpred</l>
               <l>With ſweeteſt flowres, with choyceſt poſies, ſuch</l>
               <l>As <hi>Flora</hi> ſets to make her ſofteſt bed:</l>
               <l>The dainties of each Garden, Wood and Dale,</l>
               <l>Shall kiſſe her feet, and ſay, <hi>Elizahaile.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>42</head>
               <l>The Heau'n-wrought-hangings of the flowry Queene,</l>
               <l>Along ſhall lye the paths that ſhe muſt pace;</l>
               <l>Dame <hi>Veſta's</hi> Carpets wowne with blew and greene,</l>
               <l>With red and white, ſhall think't their greateſt grace</l>
               <l>Along to lye vnder <hi>Elizaes</hi> feet,</l>
               <l>In euery high-way, and in euery ſtreeet.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:16"/>
            <lg n="43">
               <head>43</head>
               <l>Likewiſe <hi>Cybele</hi> with her holy hands,</l>
               <l>Prepares a Garland for <hi>Eliza's</hi> day,</l>
               <l>Of Gemmes and Flowers, the beſt in any lands,</l>
               <l>For it's her minde to crowne her Queene of May.</l>
               <l>Harke how ſhe warnes her Nymphes with ſiluer-bell,</l>
               <l>To gather flowres to crowne her <hi>Roſimell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44</head>
               <l>The musky <hi>Roſe,</hi> the <hi>Mari-gold</hi> and <hi>Lilly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Tulipan,</hi> the gallant <hi>Gilly-flowre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Pinke,</hi> the <hi>Primroſe, Panſe</hi> and <hi>Daffadilly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The flowry Girles fetch home vnto her bowre:</l>
               <l>Each flowre ſhe ſorts, as they do moſt excell,</l>
               <l>To crowne the head of honour'd <hi>Roſimell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <head>45</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cybele</hi> enſtiled the mother of the Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (belike) ſhee was the firſt Woman that euer bare Kings in her belly, was pictured ſitting in a Chariot drawne with Lyons, crowned and clothed with gold and precious ſtones. See <hi>Albricus</hi> in his booke <hi>de Imaginibus Deorum.</hi> The May garland that ſhe makes for <hi>Eliza,</hi> conſiſteth of nine choyce Flowres, and nine precious ſtones, repreſenting the ſtarres of <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Northerne Crowne, being nine in number, according to <hi>Ouidius, Hyginus,</hi> and <hi>Germanicus Caeſar</hi> writing vpon the Aſtronomy of <hi>Aratus.</hi>
                  </note>To euery flowre ſhe ioynes an Orient Gemme,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Diamond,</hi> the <hi>Saphire, Chryſolite,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Emerald,</hi> the <hi>Topaz,</hi> th'<hi>Opall</hi> then,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Turcas, lacynth,</hi> and the <hi>Margarite:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then in her Coach, with Lyons drawne, ſhe hies</l>
               <l>To <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> more glanſing then the skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>46</head>
               <l>Loe how ſhe comes, attir'd in greateſt ſtate,</l>
               <l>Attended on of all the flowry crew.</l>
               <l>The Hilly-vally-Nymphes ſo nice and neat,</l>
               <l>Some in their kirtles greene, ſome in their blew;</l>
               <l>With violet Skarfes to vaile each Lilly-face,</l>
               <l>Till all vnuaile before <hi>Eliza's</hi> Grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:16"/>
            <lg n="47">
               <head>47</head>
               <l>The Syluan <hi>Pan</hi> is gone to <hi>Paleſtine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Deiope,</hi> to bring a paire of Trees</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Palmes</hi> of both kindes for our paire-<hi>Palatine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make two May-poles to preſent their eyes:</l>
               <l>Which ſo they plant, that their leau'd tops may meet,</l>
               <l>And cheere each other with their kiſſes ſweet:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <head>48</head>
               <l>For Heau'n and Earth delight to ſee together</l>
               <l>Such as they ioyne by holy bands of loue,</l>
               <l>And would haue each one for to cheere another;</l>
               <l>Whereas ſad abſence doth full often proue</l>
               <l>The breake of hearts, the married couples bane,</l>
               <l>Which ſtrongeſt loue in many breaſts hath ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>49</head>
               <l>A ſigne whereof wiſe Nature doth vs ſhow</l>
               <l>In the <hi>Palme-trees,</hi> which being ſet aſunder</l>
               <l>From mutuall ſight, no fruit is ſeene to grow</l>
               <l>Of either kinde; but faint, as if ſome thunder</l>
               <l>Had blaſted both; they pine and droope as dead,</l>
               <l>And haue no heart once to hold vp their head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>50</head>
               <l>But looke how ſoone that they may ſee each other,</l>
               <l>Or that the winde doth duſt betweene them driue,</l>
               <l>As ſoone both he and ſhe their hearts recouer,</l>
               <l>Both flouriſh faſt, both beare fruit and reuiue:</l>
               <l>As they would kiſſe, their leauie lippes they moue;</l>
               <l>Thus doe the <hi>Palmes</hi> teach marryed folkes to loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
               <head>51</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plinius, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus, Diopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Pontanus,</hi> and others doe write, that there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſecret ſence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial loue betweene the Palmes, Male and Female, and that ſo vehement and earneſt, that they do commonly droope, languiſh, and wax barren, except that they may either rouch, or at leaſt ſee one another; and <hi>Theophraſtus, Herodotus,</hi> and <hi>Athenaeus</hi> do witneſſe, how that both fertility and maturity are much aduanced and furthered in the Female-palme by the meanes of the flowre and fruite of the Male-palme tied thereunto, or yet if the duſt and powder of the Hee-palme be ſpread thereupon: and if two Palmes Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male be planted on the two-ſides of a Brooke or Riuer, the one ouer againſt the other, they will ſtretch out their boughes and branches one to another, as if they would kiſſe or embrace, and therefore the learned <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Greekes,</hi> make the Palmes to bee the Heroglyphicke or enſigne of loue betweene man and wife. The Palme is likewiſe the Symbole of a godly life, according to S. <hi>Eucherius,</hi> becauſe, whereas all other Trees, are ſeene to be ſmaller aboue, and greater below; the Palme contrary-wiſe is ſmaller be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and greater aboue; reſembling the godly and deuote man, or woman, who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies great and ſtrong in things heauenly which are aboue, but ſmall and weake in things earthly which are below. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> makes the Palme to be the Symbole of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> of our Lords Croſſe: Laſtly, according to the common-conſent of both Philoſophers and Diuines, it is the ſymbole, or ſigne, of triumphant victory, becauſe as <hi>Ariſtoteles, Theophraſtus, Plutarchus, Gellius</hi> and others do deliuer, it hath this admirable property, that if a great and huge weight of ſtones bee laid vpon the backe thereof, it doth not yeeld, or bow downe-wards, as other Trees do, but it bendeth vp-wards, and riſeth vp againſt the weight arch-wiſe; of the which excellent Tree, our Poem, called a myſticall May-pole, preſented to King <hi>Iames,</hi> makes further mention.</note>
                  <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> doth celebrate a paire</l>
               <l>Of ſuch kinde <hi>Palmes:</hi> the like <hi>Pontanus</hi> writes</l>
               <l>Of two ſuch other trees both freſh and faire;</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Calabrie,</hi> which were the cheife delights,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brunduſe</hi> the one, <hi>Hydrunt</hi> the other bred,</l>
               <l>Both for their loues are highly honored.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:17"/>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>52</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The three Graces are imagined to be three yong comely and graceful God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes, going together, linkt arme in arme, whereof reade more in <hi>Phornutus, de Natura Deorum</hi> and others.</note>Neere <hi>Heidelberge</hi> the <hi>Graces</hi> three together</l>
               <l>Link't arme in arme, ſhall grac'd <hi>Eliza</hi> greet,</l>
               <l>Bleſſing the day that brought her Graces thither,</l>
               <l>(For in her face the choiſeſt graces meete)</l>
               <l>Which Siſters three come danſing o're the Greenes,</l>
               <l>In grace and face much like three <hi>Britiſh</hi> Queenes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <head>53</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aglaia</hi> bright, when firſt I her behold,</l>
               <l>Me thinkes I ſee ſweete <hi>Scotlands</hi> heire, Queene <hi>Mary,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such as ſhe was, when all deckt vp in gold,</l>
               <l>The Dolphin <hi>Francis</hi> did her gladly marry</l>
               <l>In <hi>Maries</hi> Church enſtiled <hi>Noſtredame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where firſt was ſung their <hi>Hymens</hi> Hymne and Pſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:17"/>
            <lg n="54">
               <head>54</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euphroſynë</hi> when next I her conſider,</l>
               <l>Lookes like all-lou'd <hi>Eliza, Englands</hi> Queene,</l>
               <l>When ſhe was wooed of th'other <hi>Francis</hi> brother,</l>
               <l>Nam'd <hi>Francis Monſieur;</hi> ſuch as haue her ſeene,</l>
               <l>Do ſay forſooth, this land borne neuer hath</l>
               <l>A gracefuller then Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <head>55</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thalia</hi> doth the face and grace preſent</l>
               <l>Of gracefull <hi>Anne,</hi> Queene of <hi>Great Britannie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such as ſhe was when King <hi>lames</hi> to her went</l>
               <l>Beyond the ſea, to wed her ſolemnly:</l>
               <l>Who as ſhe hath the firſt twaines Titles ioyn'd,</l>
               <l>So their two worths ſhe hath in her combin'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="56">
               <head>56</head>
               <l>Thus the three Graces, in moſt gladſome guiſe</l>
               <l>In the three faces of three famous Queenes;</l>
               <l>Link't arme in arme in roſie weed them hyes</l>
               <l>Leaping and dancing or'e the downes and greenes:</l>
               <l>And thus they ſing; <hi>All baile Eliza faire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grand-mothers, Mothers, and God-mothers heire.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="57">
               <head>57</head>
               <l>Thrice gracefull Lady welcome to our Clime,</l>
               <l>Welcome the Flowre and Roſe of <hi>Britanny,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Welcome the hope and honour of our time,</l>
               <l>Welcome the pearle and praiſe of <hi>Germany:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Long may thy face grace <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Rhine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both vs and ours, ſo may thy <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="58">
               <head>58</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The three <hi>Graces</hi> are brought in preſenting three Roſes, the firſt a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle white one, the ſecond a ſingle red one, the third a double one, white and red together; becauſe that the Roſe is held of the learned to be the Hierogliphicke, Symbole, or ſigne of gracefulneſſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and loue: And the Philoſophers doe thinke that the odour, and colour thereof doth proceed from the influence of the gracefull Planet <hi>Venus.</hi> The <hi>Mages,</hi> or <hi>Sages</hi> of the <hi>Indians,</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> did much vſe the Roſe, with the oyle and water thereof, to conciliate the gracefull &amp; fauourable aſpect of Kings, Queenes, Princes &amp; Potentates. And we reade how that <hi>Aelius Verus,</hi> the Emperour, was wont to lye on a bed of Roſes, as it were to draw from thence a kinde of gracefull influence, which hee might after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards impart to his people. Read <hi>Orus Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Pierius</hi> in their Hierogliphickes.</note>Each of the three a Roſe to her preſents,</l>
               <l>The firſt a white Roſe in milke-white array;</l>
               <l>The next in her carnation veſtiments,</l>
               <l>A red-carnation Roſe, ſweet, freſh and gay;</l>
               <l>The third, whoſe habit is of white-red hue,</l>
               <l>A white-red Roſe, and ſaies: <hi>Sweet Roſe adue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:18"/>
            <lg n="59">
               <head>59</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">In the ancient enſigne of <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge</hi> was painted a moſt comely and gracefull Nymph, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on a Myrtle-hill, and at a freſh fountaine there. A monument thereof is to bee ſeene in Marble; for a crowned Lyon, or Lyoneſſe holds in its pawes a Scutchion, in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome whereof is the ſaid Myrtle Nymph, painted with a bundle of Myrtle-berries in her hand. Read hereof <hi>Paulus Meliſſus,</hi> and <hi>Marquardus Freiherus</hi>
                  </note>Braue <hi>Heidelbergs</hi> renowned Myrtle-Nymph,</l>
               <l>Whoſe comely face all commers do behold</l>
               <l>With much delight, at the freſh ſpringing lymph,</l>
               <l>That fountaine faire, ſo ſweet, ſo cleere, ſo cold:</l>
               <l>Mounted vpon her Lyoneſſe of ſtate,</l>
               <l>Shall meet <hi>Eliza</hi> at the Cities gate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="60">
               <head>60</head>
               <l>The Nymph no ſooner ſees <hi>Eliza</hi> bright,</l>
               <l>But all amaz'd ſhe bids her Lyon ſtay,</l>
               <l>For I (quoth ſhe) muſt from thy backe alight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tam-Iſis</hi> Nymph for to adore to day.</l>
               <l>Stand ſtill proud ſteed, for both muſt I and thou,</l>
               <l>This bliſſe-ſtill-day before <hi>Eliza</hi> bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="61">
               <head>61</head>
               <l>Vncrowne thy head of thy gold Diadem,</l>
               <l>Thou beſt of beaſts, thou ſtately Lyon-queene,</l>
               <l>For it is due vnto a greater Dame,</l>
               <l>A ſweeter yet then euer thou haſt ſeene.</l>
               <l>See how ſhe doth with glanſing glory ſhine,</l>
               <l>Go honour her, and crowne her Queene of <hi>Rhine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:18"/>
            <lg n="62">
               <head>62</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Lyon is the Symbole of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who is called <hi>the Lyon of the Tribe of Iuda</hi> in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation.</hi> And hee is a <hi>Lilly-Lyon,</hi> becauſe <hi>he feedeth among the Lillies,</hi> as it is in the <hi>Canticles.</hi> And the Lyon inuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Lilies, is the Royall badge of our Soueraigne. The Lyon rampant is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the badge both of the Palatine Princes, and of the princely houſe of <hi>Howards,</hi> in whoſe Illuſtrious diſcent I haue found 12 of the ſame Emperours, and twiſe 12 of the ſame Kings, which doe occurre in the Pedigrees common to King <hi>Iames</hi> and Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> as ſhall bee (God willing) ſhewed other-where. The firſt that ere bare the Lyon for his badge, was <hi>Hercules</hi> the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> as we may gather out of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> and <hi>Diodorus.</hi> And <hi>Gathelus,</hi> who was of the ſame bloud that <hi>Hercules</hi> was of, brought this Enſigne firſt into <hi>Britanny;</hi> and <hi>Agamemnon</hi> king of the <hi>Argiues,</hi> who was of the ſame bloud with <hi>Gathelus,</hi> whoſe father <hi>Argus Nilus</hi> was likewiſe King of the <hi>Argiues,</hi> and had in him vnited the <hi>Arginian</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> bloud, hee did likewiſe beare the Lyon in his ſhield, as witneſſeth <hi>Pauſanias;</hi> who telleth how that <hi>Idomenous</hi> King of <hi>Creet</hi> bare a Cocke in his Scutchion, which is eſteemed to bee the Symbole of triumphant victory: for the Lyon himſelfe, though he be the moſt magnanimous and ſtrongeſt of all beaſts, ſo that S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> with others, enſtileth him King of beaſts, yet hee ſtands in feare of the Cocke, chiefly the white, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> doth deliuer, beſides the ancients, <hi>Zoreaſter, Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Lucretius, Aelianus, Proclus,</hi> with others. The reaſon whereof <hi>Proclus</hi> thinketh to be thus, becauſe that the Cocke and the Lyon, being both of them in a certaine pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner gouerned by the influence of the Sunne, the Cocke receiueth more of the force thereof (which doth appeare by his accurate obſeruing of the times of the night and day) then the Lyon doth, and therefore being in that reſpect his inferiour, the law of Nature tyeth him to reuere and feare the Cocke as his ſuperiour. Others doe adde, that the Cocke repreſenteth the power Coeleſtiall and Spirituall; and the Lyon the power terreſtriall and temporall. Moreouer the Lyon is the Simbole, or Enſigne, not onely of magnanimity and ſtrength, and of religious feare, but alſo of vigilancy and watchfulneſſe; becauſe that according to the common conſent of the learned, namely <hi>Ariſtoteles, Manethon, Plinius, Aelianus, Plutarchus,</hi> and <hi>Macrobius,</hi> hee ſleepeth with his eyes open, which do likewiſe ſhine as full of light and withall ſtirreth his taile in the meane time that hee is aſleepe, of which hee is neuer ouercome. The Lyon is likewiſe the Symbole of Clemency, becauſe among all the wilde beaſts he alone ſpareth ſuch perſons as do proſtrate themſelues before him, and by ſignes and ſpeeches do pray him to ſhew pitty, as <hi>Plinius, Aelianus</hi> and others do witneſſe. It is alſo the Symbole of iuſt reuenge, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſaid Authors, together with <hi>Oci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>na,</hi> doe deliuer, he marketh moſt diligently ſuch as inuade him, and hurt him; and though he bee in neuer ſo great a throng, if he can, he purſueth him, and killeth him; whereas hee onely terrifieth, or throweth downe the man that had onely aimed at him, but not hurt him. <hi>Hanno</hi> of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> was the firſt man that tamed the Lyon, which hee vſed in the bearing of his bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage. <hi>Berenice</hi> Queene of <hi>Egypt</hi> had a Lyon ſo tame, that ſhe would ſuffer him to licke her face, and eate with her at the Table. Others haue taken tame Lyons to the field to fight againſt their enemies. But aboue all, the hiſtory of <hi>Androcles,</hi> reported by <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus,</hi> and <hi>Gellius,</hi> is notable, whom a Lyon fed three yeares in the time hee was fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiue; and afterwards being both taken, not onely ſpared, when as hee was caſten to him for his prey, but alſo protected him from the the furious inuaſion of a Libbard, and folded himſelfe at his feet, &amp; ſhewed all the ſignes of amity that he could, though ſome good ſpace had paſt ſince they had liued together in the den. The ground and cauſe of all the which affection, was for that <hi>Androcles</hi> had pulled a thorne out of the poore Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons foote, and healed his ſoare, at the very firſt time that he chanced to repoſe himſelfe in the faid den, not caring what became of him. The which matter beeing ſignified to <hi>Caeſar, Androcles</hi> was reſtored to his liberty, and the Lyon his old Hoſt giuen him for his guerdon, of whom it was thus commonly ſaid when as they went along the ſtreets; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the man who was the Lyons Phyſitian, and the Lyon who was the mans Hoſt.</hi>
                  </note>The Lilly-lyon of the <hi>North</hi> to day,</l>
               <l>Sends to our Towne his onely daughter deere,</l>
               <l>Vpon her Crowne to beare thy crowne away:</l>
               <l>Wherefore be ſure, ſo ſoone as thou comes neere</l>
               <l>To Norths great Lyons bright <hi>Elizabelle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou quit thy Crowne, and call her <hi>Lyonnelle.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:19"/>
            <lg n="63">
               <head>63</head>
               <l>Come after me, and do all this and more,</l>
               <l>For this is but the thouſandth of her due,</l>
               <l>Sith that the worth of all that went before</l>
               <l>She hath in her; I tell the thing that's true,</l>
               <l>In ſigne whereof I ſweare by <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Venus,</hi> the Lady of loue, is the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Myrtle-tree, &amp; as <hi>Nicander</hi> writeth, ſhee ware a Myrtle garland the day ſhee wan the Golden Apple by the iudgement of <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </note> Myrtle-queene,</l>
               <l>I'le do the thing that neuer yet was ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="64">
               <head>64</head>
               <l>For her ſweet ſake my well ſhall ſpring with wine,</l>
               <l>My ſtreaming ſpouts to day ſhall not grow dry,</l>
               <l>But run ſuch liquor as the land of <hi>Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth brue for the beſt mouthes of Maieſty.</l>
               <l>And if I had as many pearles as vines,</l>
               <l>They ſhould turne drinke to theſe two Valentines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="65">
               <head>65</head>
               <l>The beſt <hi>Ambroſie</hi> euer <hi>Bacchus</hi> brew'd,</l>
               <l>Fetcht from <hi>Palerme</hi> of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Greece;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe beauties bright ſhall be therewith bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w'd,</l>
               <l>Which do attend vpon this golden fleece:</l>
               <l>The ſtrangeſt tunne that euer wight did ſee,</l>
               <l>To welcome them, ſhall run with <hi>Malmeſie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:19"/>
            <lg n="66">
               <head>66</head>
               <l>The Myrtle-bunch that I haue borne ſo long</l>
               <l>With great applauſe <hi>Eliza's</hi> lap ſhall fill;</l>
               <l>For to <hi>Tamiſis</hi> Nymph it doth belong</l>
               <l>Who now's the Nymph of this our Myrtle-hill:</l>
               <l>Wherefore let Hils and Dales reſound her fame,</l>
               <l>Sith all the Nymphes muſt her <hi>Myrtilla</hi> name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="67">
               <head>67</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Becauſe the Myrtles of <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge</hi> are but wilde, low ſhrubs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Nymphe to congratulate <hi>Eliza,</hi> wiſheth ſhee had the Myrtle-tree, which <hi>Plinius</hi> and others do tell once grew in old <hi>Romes</hi> firſt plot, and ſome of thoſe Myrtles of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which according to <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> and <hi>Athenaeus</hi> are the moſt fragrant of all other. The greater Myrtle groweth plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and in <hi>Italy,</hi> about <hi>Naples,</hi> the ſmaller in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> the leaues are alwaies greene, the flowres faire and white. It is the onely Tree that yeeldeth both oyle and wine, alſo the Myrtle-berries of old time ſerued in ſteed of pepper. It doth likewiſe affoord a kind of ſweete perfume to hee burned; it was choſen to make an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, and to rarefie the marriage betweene the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Sabins,</hi> becauſe <hi>Venus</hi> is the patroneſſe thereof. Hence it is, that the wiſe <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Greekes</hi> haue made the Myrtle-tree to bee the Symbole of matrimoniall loue; and in a country of <hi>Greece</hi> called <hi>Trezenie,</hi> there is a kind of Myrtle whoſe leaues are full of holes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the wounds and heart-holes of languiſhing louers. It is like-wiſe the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole or Enſigne of ſuch honeſt mirth and gladneſſe, as is vſed at Banquets and Feaſts; For of old times, as <hi>Plutarchus</hi> and <hi>Horatius</hi> do teſtifie, at Banquets, a branch of Myrtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle went round about the Table, whereby, each one of the Feaſters was inuited to ſing ſome honeſt ſong to reioyce the company: And the Myrtle-Nymph of <hi>Heidelberge</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth that her Cittizens ſhould renew, or repreſent, this old cuſtome at their Feaſts made in honour of <hi>Elizabeths</hi> arriuall, by making her Myrtle-berry in ſteed of a Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branch go round about the Table to inuire them to ſing their beſt ſongs for <hi>Elizabeths</hi> ſake. The ſame Nymph like-wiſe promiſeth that her Myrtle-berries at <hi>Eliza's</hi> comming ſhall haue the ſame vertue that the Myrtle-rod, by <hi>Plinius</hi> and others, is reported to haue; which is to chaſe all wearineſſe from folkes limmes, come they neuer ſo far off to ſee <hi>Eliza's</hi> ſolemnities.</note>Or if I had the Myrtle-tree that ſtood</l>
               <l>In <hi>Romes</hi> firſt plot, hard by Mount-<hi>Palatine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or yet thoſe Myrtles nie to <hi>Nilus</hi> floud</l>
               <l>Of fragrant ſmell, which there are to be ſeene:</l>
               <l>A Myrtle-May-pole, with a Myrtle-wreath</l>
               <l>Should grace the gates of lou'd <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:20"/>
            <lg n="68">
               <head>68</head>
               <l>Oh, if I had the hands for to aduance</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Myrtilla's</hi> ſtate amidſt as many Townes,</l>
               <l>As their are Myrtle-trees in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Italy,</hi> or yet in <hi>Germans</hi> bound;</l>
               <l>All ſhould be hers to twiſe ten thouſand ſcore;</l>
               <l>For why, her worth deſerues as much and more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="69">
               <head>69</head>
               <l>Yet for a ſigne, I wiſh her all the hap</l>
               <l>Which this my Myrtle-emblems ſence reſounds;</l>
               <l>Lo how I lay into her louely lap,</l>
               <l>As many berries as be Towers or Townes</l>
               <l>Twixt pureſt <hi>Rheine,</hi> and fruitfull <hi>Nilus</hi> Floud,</l>
               <l>About whoſe Bankes ſo many Myrtles ſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="70">
               <head>70</head>
               <l>Yee Virgin troupes, which flocke within our wals</l>
               <l>From many miles to view <hi>Myrtilla's</hi> glory;</l>
               <l>Forget not when my ſhoure of Berries fals</l>
               <l>Vpon her cloaths to catch each Myrtle-berry:</l>
               <l>This Berry ſhall all wearineſſe debarre</l>
               <l>From your ſoft limmes, tho yee come neere ſo farre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="71">
               <head>71</head>
               <l>Each worthy Burgeſſe of the Myrtle-towne</l>
               <l>Keepe yee a feaſt in honour of this day;</l>
               <l>Call all your poore to ſing and dance the round,</l>
               <l>And ſtriue who ſhall the Berry beare away:</l>
               <l>At all your feaſts, this Berry yee preſent,</l>
               <l>In ſigne of gladneſſe, glee, and merriment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="72">
               <head>72</head>
               <l>The Myrtle-bough befits <note n="*" place="margin">The Myrtle-Tree, ſaith <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>naus,</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Myrſine</hi> in <hi>Greek,</hi> becauſe of a yong La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in <hi>Athens</hi> ſo named, who in beauty excelled all the Laſſes and Ladies of that Citty, and in ſtrength and Actiuity all the luſty Lads and Gallants of <hi>Greece;</hi> for the which ſhee was tenderly beloued of <hi>Minerua,</hi> or <hi>Pallas,</hi> the Patroneſſe of Wiſedome and Valour, who willed her to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies preſent at Turney and Tilt, running, vauting, and other ſuch exerciſes of Armes, to the end that fitting as Iudge of their Actiuity, ſhee might giue the Garland-prize to ſuch as beſt deſerued the ſame. But ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which were vanquiſhed, were ſo much diſpleaſed with her iudgement, that they ſlue her. The which thing ſo ſoon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as <hi>Pallas</hi> perceiued, ſhe cauſed the ſweete Myrtle to ſpring vp out of her bloud, and called it <hi>Myrſine,</hi> in honour and remembrance of her.</note>
                  <hi>Myrſina's</hi> Peere</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza</hi> lou'd, in whom the worth doth dwell,</l>
               <l>Which once <hi>Myrſina</hi> had <hi>Minerua's</hi> deere,</l>
               <l>That did in wit and valour both excell:</l>
               <l>Shee gaue the prize as iudge of Chiualrie</l>
               <l>Till her ſweete bloud turn'd to a Myrtle-tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:20"/>
            <lg n="73">
               <head>73</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Ioue</hi> vouchſafe vs once to ſee the day</l>
               <l>When we ſhall reape ſuch honour'd victory</l>
               <l>Vpon proud <hi>Turkes,</hi> that our <hi>Myrſina</hi> may</l>
               <l>Sit downe to iudge of feats of Chiualry:</l>
               <l>As once ſhee did, at <hi>Henries</hi> ſports of warre,</l>
               <l>Reward two Wights, <hi>Montgomry, Lochinwarre.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="74">
               <head>74</head>
               <l>When I conſider the late fire-fight,</l>
               <l>Shew'd on the Thames twixt Chriſten-men and Turkes,</l>
               <l>And how a Turke by kindled Cannons might</l>
               <l>Loſt both his hands; met-thinkes that in it lurkes</l>
               <l>This lucky ſigne; th'vnited Northerne States</l>
               <l>Out of Turks hands ſhall wring their Townes and ſeats.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="75">
               <head>75</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Of ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, God-willing, ſhal be aboundantly ſpoken in our <hi>Sibylla Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica;</hi> in the meane time, it is to be noted, that <hi>Iohannes Leunclauius</hi> in the Preface of his <hi>Muſſulmane</hi> Hiſtory, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the Prince-electors, doth deliuer, how that old Oracles do promiſe that the Turke ſhall bee finally and totally ouer-throwne at the Riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> by the vnited forces of three Kings. And <hi>Michael Noſtradamus</hi> telleth, how that the day ſhall be, when the Princes of the Pole-article, or the North, to the number of ſixe, ſhall ioyne with the chiefe, or Prince of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that they ſhall bring great terror and tribulation to the <hi>Mahumetane</hi> Turkes. Laſtly, the moſt glorious Propheſie that I find of any Prince, is of a Prince of the name of <hi>Charles,</hi> the which, <hi>Carion</hi> in his Chronicle hath applyed to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and Emperour; but truely, that moſt worthy, valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and victorious Prince hath left the accompliſhment thereof to ſome other <hi>Charles</hi> then himſelfe, as the tenure of the prediction conferred with his deedes, howſoeuer glorious, may teſtifie: and it hath bene alwaies my moſt ardent wiſh euer ſince I began to be ſome-what curious in this kind, that that Propheſie alledged by <hi>Carion</hi> out of the old Chronicles of <hi>Magdeburg,</hi> might haue one day his full accompliſhment in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and that as he doth Symbolize with <hi>Caſtriote, alias Scanderbeg,</hi> in the common ſtile of Prince, or Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> ſo may hee like-wiſe with him in his Proweſſe againſt the Turkes, and in his Titles of Chriſts Champion, and the terrour of Turkes. Whereof, who will, may read more in our Poem made vpon Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Natiuity.</note>No leſſe is promis'd by old Propheſies,</l>
               <l>Which wee haue ſeene in <hi>Latine, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With other tongues, which promiſe victories</l>
               <l>To Northerne hands, how they combin'd ſhall drench</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in a foaming floud</l>
               <l>Which ſhall be made of ſpilt Barbarian bloud.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:21"/>
            <lg n="76">
               <head>76</head>
               <l>O happy ſight to ſee Prince <hi>Charles</hi> one day</l>
               <l>Together with the States of <hi>Germany,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Againſt proud Turkes his Banner to diſplay</l>
               <l>That as he's nam'd the Duke of <hi>Albany;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So men may him a <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> enſtile,</l>
               <l>Th'horrour of Turkes, the <hi>Hercles</hi> of this Ile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="77">
               <head>77</head>
               <l>CHRIST IESVS name ſweete <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Britanny</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> thy Champion, and thy Knight,</l>
               <l>Adde vnto his one Northerne <hi>Albany,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sixe <hi>Albanies;</hi> chooſe him thy fields to fight</l>
               <l>'Gainſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and grant him for his hire,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Towne, with the proud Turkes Empire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="78">
               <head>78</head>
               <l>That our <hi>Myrſina</hi> may her Brother Crowne</l>
               <l>With Palmy-wreath in ſigne of victory,</l>
               <l>And like <hi>Debora</hi> ſing his high renowne,</l>
               <l>Thanking great <hi>loue</hi> for the felicity;</l>
               <l>It pleas'd him to her brother <hi>Charles</hi> to giue,</l>
               <l>In whoſe ſweete face lou'd <hi>Henry</hi> ſtill doth liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:21"/>
            <lg n="79">
               <head>79</head>
               <l>The Maids and Matrons ſhall with cheerefull voyce</l>
               <l>Extoll <hi>Myrſina</hi> and her honour raiſe</l>
               <l>Vp to the skies; both aged men and boies</l>
               <l>Shall hop and danſe, and loud reſound her praiſe;</l>
               <l>Agniſing her to be the ſweeteſt Wight</l>
               <l>That euer lodg'd in <hi>Heidelberge</hi> all night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="80">
               <head>80</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Three Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours 3 daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of the name of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilde</hi> or <hi>Maud,</hi> haue ben mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to three <hi>Palatine</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the firſt <hi>Mathildis</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Otho</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Duke of <hi>Saxe</hi> and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Siffrid</hi> Prince <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> the ſecond, was the daughter of <hi>Rodulph</hi> the firſt, Earle of <hi>Habſpurg</hi> and Emperour, married to Prince <hi>Lodowicke,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Seuere;</hi> &amp; the third <hi>Mathildis</hi> was the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Adolph</hi> Earle of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> and Emperour, married to <hi>Rodolph</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine:</hi> And as for Kings daughters that haue bene married to the <hi>Palatines,</hi> we reade in <hi>Henninges, Dauid Rorarius,</hi> and <hi>Marquardus Freherus,</hi> how that <hi>Blanch,</hi> the eldeſt daughter of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fourth King of <hi>England,</hi> was the firſt wife of <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the fourth, Prince <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Robert</hi> the Emperour, who, as <hi>Fabian</hi> and <hi>Cooper</hi> in their Chronicles doe write, came heere into <hi>England, Anno,</hi> 1403, and was receiued of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> with great Triumph. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Writers, though they agree that the ſaid Lady <hi>Blanch</hi> was married about this time to a Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> and hee the Emperours ſonne, yet they make no particular mention of any ſuch Match, as the aboue named <hi>Germaines</hi> do auouch, but rather otherwiſe: <hi>Ranulph</hi> of <hi>Cheſter, Walſingham, Fabian,</hi> and <hi>Stow,</hi> doe not expreſſe the Dukes name that married her; <hi>Polydorus</hi> erroniouſly calleth him <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſonne to the Duke of <hi>Bauier; Hal,</hi> and <hi>Hollinſhed</hi> name him <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Emperour, but this could not be; for both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Genelogicians write, that the ſaid Duke <hi>William</hi> married <hi>Maud</hi> daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> whoſe other daughter <hi>Blanch</hi> married <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gant</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> and in her right, Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and that ſhe ſuruiued her husband foure yeares, and that he died <hi>Anno</hi> 1377. ſome 25. yeares before the marriage of <hi>Blanch,</hi> the eldeſt daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth; who, according to the truth, was married to <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Robert</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> and Emperour, who had bene choſen but a ſhort ſpace before, by the Electors, and came heere into <hi>England,</hi> as is ſaid aboue. And as for the reſt of the Kings daughters, mentioned in the Poem, <hi>Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mille</hi> of <hi>Boheme,</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Primiſlay</hi> the 2. King of <hi>Boheme,</hi> and of <hi>Conſtance</hi> his wife, the daughter of <hi>Bela</hi> the third, King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſhee was married to <hi>Lodowick</hi> the father of <hi>Otho</hi> the <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Bauiere. Beatrice</hi> of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilie,</hi> wife to <hi>Robert</hi> the ſecond, Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Fredericke</hi> King of <hi>Sicilie,</hi> according to <hi>Cuſpinianus, Carion, Rheuſnerus, Marquardus</hi> and <hi>Brunnius:</hi> as for <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterus,</hi> he doth not expreſſe his propper name, but <hi>Henninges,</hi> and <hi>Albizius</hi> make her the daughter of King <hi>Peter. Dorothie</hi> of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> the wife of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Denmarke. Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Hungary</hi> was wife to <hi>Heary</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> the yonger brother of <hi>Lodowicke</hi> called the <hi>Seuere,</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and Daughter and Heire of <hi>Bela,</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>Hungary.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Polony,</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Conrade,</hi> Prince of <hi>Poland,</hi> and one of the three wiues of the fore-ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the <hi>Seuere,</hi> ſo called, for that out of an vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete humor of iealouſly, hee practiſed a filthy cruelty vpon his wife <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Brabant,</hi> in cauſing her head to bee cut off, for that ſhee had written a letter to a Captaine of his owne, named <hi>Henry Rucco,</hi> which came into his hands: for the which abhominable fact, hee was ſo terrified with an horrible viſion by night, that his head became before the next morning as white as wooll, ſo that hee repenting him of his iealouſy and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, founded the Monaſtery of <hi>Furſtenfield,</hi> and endowed the ſame with rich poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as <hi>Cuſpinianus</hi> and <hi>Henninges</hi> do write. Thus wee ſee, how that it fared much more hardly with this good Lady <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Brabant,</hi> then it did, with <hi>Cunegunde</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Henry</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> maried to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, Emperour, who got leaue to purge her ſelfe of the like falſe ſuſpition, by going bare-foote (as ſhe did, without hurt) vpon a number of Plough-ſhares red hot, as the ſame <hi>Cuſpinianus</hi> with <hi>Vrſpergenſis</hi> doe write. And in <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmeſbury,</hi> and <hi>Ranulph</hi> of <hi>Cheſter</hi> wee reade how that Queene <hi>Emme,</hi> mother to King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> being accuſed of adultery with <hi>Edwin,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> purged her ſelfe in the ſame manner. Semblably wee reade in <hi>Cuſpinianus, Paulus Emylius,</hi> and <hi>Francis de Belle-foreſt,</hi> how that <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Groſſe</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> and Emperour, accuſed his wife <hi>Richarda,</hi> a daughter of <hi>Scotland,</hi> of playing falſe play with <hi>Luitwald</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vercelle</hi> in <hi>Lumbardy,</hi> her chiefe Councelor, but ſhe cleered her ſelfe to her great honour, and her iealous, yea, impotent husbands great ſhame. So did <hi>Gonilda</hi> the faire, daughter of <hi>Canute</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> accuſed to her husband <hi>Henry</hi> the third Emperour, of the like fault, who when as ſhee could find none to fight in the defence of her honeſty againſt her ſlanderous accuſer, being ſo ſtrong and of ſo huge a Statute, it pleaſed God to enſpire a little boy with <hi>Dauids</hi> courage, whom ſhee had brought out of <hi>England</hi> with her, who encountring with the reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Goliah,</hi> firſt cut his knee, and being fallen to the ground, cut off his head, and brought it to the good Empreſſe <hi>Gonilda,</hi> who thanked God with great reioyſing for working ſuch a wonder for her ſake by the hands of a boy, being of ſo low a Stature, that he was commonly called <hi>Mimecan,</hi> or the Dwarfe, as <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſsbury, Mathew</hi> of <hi>eſtminſter,</hi> and <hi>Ranulph</hi> of <hi>Cheſter</hi> haue written.</note>The three <hi>Mathilda's</hi> Girles of <hi>Caeſars</hi> three</l>
               <l>Which wedded were to Princes three of <hi>Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had not more worth, more grace, more Maieſty</l>
               <l>Then lou'd <hi>Eliza</hi> Princeſſe <hi>Palatine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blanch</hi> once a daughter of <hi>South-britanny</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVas not her match, nor <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Polony.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="81">
               <head>81</head>
               <l>Nor yet <hi>Bohemies</hi> Lady <hi>Ludomille,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Beatrice</hi> the Girle of <hi>Sicilie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor ſhe of <hi>Bauier,</hi> whom they name <hi>Sybille;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No more her Match was <hi>Denmarkes Dorothy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bauier</hi> Ladies two</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza's</hi> both might t' our <hi>Eliza</hi> bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:22"/>
            <lg n="82">
               <head>82</head>
               <l>The Muſes then of <hi>Heidelberge</hi> ſhall come</l>
               <l>Before her face, with Pamphlets full of praiſe,</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Dutch,</hi> ſome <hi>French,</hi> ſome <hi>Latine,</hi> other ſome</l>
               <l>In <hi>Greeke,</hi> her name and ſame abroad to blaſe:</l>
               <l>Some ſhall in Verſe, and other ſome in Proſe</l>
               <l>Record the worth of ſuch a gallant Roſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="83">
               <head>83</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Church-Holy-Ghoſt</hi> which <hi>Caeſar Robert</hi> fram'd</l>
               <l>Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> and King of <hi>Germany,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With his Empreſſe, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſurnam'd;</l>
               <l>When it receiues the Roſe of <hi>Britanny:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall pray great <hi>Ioue</hi> that ſhee ſee neuer death,</l>
               <l>Till ſhee bee ſtil'd Empreſſe <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="84">
               <head>84</head>
               <l>Me-thinkes I ſee how <hi>Robert</hi> from his ſhrine</l>
               <l>With his <hi>Eliza</hi> ſleeping in that place</l>
               <l>Awake to welcome their ſonnes <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wiſhing them both all health, wealth, hap, and grace:</l>
               <l>That as they both do from them iointly ſpring,</l>
               <l>So may them <hi>Ioue</hi> to all their honours bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="85">
               <head>85</head>
               <l>One thing will want, which much I wiſh were there</l>
               <l>An <hi>Organd-quior</hi> of Surpliz'd Saints to ſing,</l>
               <l>Such as we heare in <hi>Paules</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heauens, earths delight; but thou Concording King</l>
               <l>To <hi>Holy-Ghoſt-Church</hi> helpe for to reſtore</l>
               <l>Such holy-ſtate as once ſhe had before.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:23"/>
            <lg n="86">
               <head>86</head>
               <l>O if S. <hi>Giles</hi> which <hi>Edinburgers</hi> holds</l>
               <l>With <hi>Heidelbergers</hi> Holy-Ghoſt could ſing</l>
               <l>Such Organd-anthems ſhall bee ſung in <hi>Paules</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Londoners,</hi> the day that they ſhall bring</l>
               <l>This Lady home, whoſe worth and dignity</l>
               <l>Should bee ſolemniz'd of theſe Citties three.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="87">
               <head>87</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">On the left hand of <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge</hi> is a Hil called <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenberg</hi> which is by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the Hill of all Saints, where, according to <hi>Franciſcus Irenicus,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Leodius,</hi> was anciently a Temple ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in honour of all the Heathen Gods called <hi>Pantheon,</hi> like vnto that of <hi>Rome,</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in <hi>Dion Caſſius,</hi> which Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> as <hi>Platina</hi> teſtifieth, conuerted into a Church called <hi>Al-Saints.</hi>
                  </note>When firſt <hi>Myrſina</hi> mounts <hi>Pantheon</hi> Hill</l>
               <l>By <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> mee-thinkes a Lady-bright</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Panthaea</hi> nam'd, <hi>Myrſina</hi> comes vntill,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with beauty, modeſty, and might:</l>
               <l>Such as ſhe had, when her lou'd <hi>Abradate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Perſe</hi> was Lord of <hi>Suſas</hi> Lilly-ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="88">
               <head>88</head>
               <l>This Princely Dame whom <hi>Xenophon</hi> doth praiſe</l>
               <l>Both for her beauty and her chaſtity,</l>
               <l>When to King <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſhe a captiue was,</l>
               <l>Who had good proofe of her pudicity:</l>
               <l>As ſoone as ſhee doth her <hi>Myrſina</hi> meete,</l>
               <l>Shee in this manner her begins to greete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="89">
               <head>89</head>
               <l>Welcome <hi>Myrſina</hi> to <hi>Pantheon</hi> Hill,</l>
               <l>Welcome pure Pearle, whom I <hi>Panthaea</hi> loue;</l>
               <l>Welcome to me, and ſhall be euer ſtill,</l>
               <l>To Wights below, and vnto Gods aboue:</l>
               <l>Bleſt be the feete that fetcht this glaſſe to me</l>
               <l>Of thy ſweete face, wherein mine owne I ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:23"/>
            <lg n="90">
               <head>90</head>
               <l>As ardent loue may laſt betweene you twaine,</l>
               <l>As did 'twixt me, and my deere <hi>Abradate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioue</hi> from aboue his bleſſings powre amaine</l>
               <l>Downe on your heads, and make ſo mount your ſtate</l>
               <l>Amongs your Peeres, as much as <hi>Iuno's Lilly</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Surmounts the <hi>Primroſe, Panſe</hi> or <hi>Daffadilly.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="91">
               <head>91</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Alceſtis</hi> loued ſo entirely &amp; deerely her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing husband <hi>Admetus,</hi> King of <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> that ſhe chooſed to die, thereby to deliuer her ſaid husband from imminent death, as is in <hi>Euripides,</hi> or as writeth <hi>Palapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> more probably, that ſhee made herſelfe the captiue of <hi>Accaſtus,</hi> to deliuer her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band from his captiuity, who was afterwards deliuered by <hi>Hercules,</hi> and reſtored to her louing husband. And as for <hi>Pericles,</hi> Prince of <hi>Athens,</hi> he loued ſo deerely his louing <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſia,</hi> that he neuer went out a doores from her, but he kiſſed her, as writes <hi>Plutarchus.</hi>
                  </note>Such vnquench't fire as once the breaſts did burne</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Admetus</hi> and his <hi>Alceſtis</hi> deere,</l>
               <l>Burne both your breaſts till both to aſhes turne,</l>
               <l>Or both turne ſtarres amidſt pure <hi>Venus</hi> ſpheare:</l>
               <l>So liue, ſo loue, that time you ſurname may</l>
               <l>A <hi>Pericles,</hi> and an <hi>Aſpaſia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="92">
               <head>92</head>
               <l>Then for a token of her loue ſo deere,</l>
               <l>Towards <hi>Myrſina,</hi> for whoſe ſake ſhe came,</l>
               <l>She her bequeathes a Lilly-crowne to weare,</l>
               <l>And her entreates not to neglect the ſame:</l>
               <l>And that this ſigne her grace ſhould neuer leaue,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Panthaea,</hi> who her that garland gaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="93">
               <head>93</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Lilly is the King of Flowers, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard both of the faireneſſe, &amp; the tallneſſe thereof. In <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons Canticles</hi> it is the Symbole of our Sauiour, In S. <hi>Hilary</hi> it is the Symbole of the glorious Angels. It is likewiſe the Symbole, or Enſigne of publicke hope, as may appeare by the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Medals of <hi>Alexander Pius, Aemilianus, Claudius, Tiberius, Adrianus,</hi> and others. Finally, it is the Symbole of beauty and pudicity, according to S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> and great ſtore there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of did grow in the <hi>Perſian</hi> fields about <hi>Suſa,</hi> the delicate and moſt ſweet winter-ſeat of the Kings of <hi>Perſia.</hi> The which Cities name is by interpretation, a Lilly, as <hi>Athenaeus</hi> doth witneſſe, and was ſo named according to the teſtimony of <hi>Stephanus in Vrbibus,</hi> from the abound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce of faire Lillies there growing. It was once the Citty of <hi>Abradate</hi> and <hi>Panthaea,</hi> who are ſo highly praiſed by <hi>Xenophon,</hi> &amp; afterwards by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierom.</hi> When <hi>Cyrus</hi> had ouercome the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> this <hi>Perſian</hi> Princeſſe was taken, her husband <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date,</hi> Prince of <hi>Suſa,</hi> being then abſent in <hi>Bactria,</hi> hee being the moſt worthy and valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Chiefetaine of his time, and ſhe both the moſt vertuous and the moſt beauteous Lady of all <hi>Aſia;</hi> who when as ſome of King <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Courtiers did comfort her the beſt way they could, telling her amongs other matters, that in ſteed of an <hi>Abradate,</hi> ſhe was to be honoured with the loue and ſociety of a <hi>Cyrus,</hi> no ſooner heard ſhe theſe words, but ſhe began to beate her breaſt, to teare her haire, and to rent her cloathes, and vaile from top to toe, taking vp amids her mournfull maids, a moſt bitter lamentation. The conſideration of whoſe incomparable beauty and worth, made <hi>Cyrus</hi> to forbeare to come into her ſight, as fearing to be ouercome with the vigour of her vertue. Her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being returned, and hauing receiued tokens from her, with letters, letting him to vnderſtand, how that he ſhould be welcome to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> he made all poſſible haſte of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Court, accompanied with a thouſand horſemen in goodly array. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom <hi>Panthaea</hi> hauing made report of the religion, vertue, temperancy, continency and compaſſion of King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> ſhewed in her behalfe, when as it lay in his power to doe with her what he would, <hi>Abradate</hi> replied, ſaying; and what wouldſt thou (my deere <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaea</hi>) that I did to requite theſe curteſies of <hi>Cyrus?</hi> Who anſwered; what ſhouldſt thou do elſe (my deere <hi>Abradate</hi>) but follow the footſteps of his vertue, in labouring to be like vnto ſo worthy a wight. And being come before <hi>Cyrus,</hi> he ſaith; for the ineſtimable curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie thou haſt ſhewed in the behalfe of my <hi>Panthaea,</hi> thy priſoner, I can make thee no other requitall, but offer vnto thee my ſelfe, my friendſhip, my ſociety and ſeruice euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, for the aduancing of thine honor. And afterwards, when as <hi>Abradate</hi> was to go to fight againſt the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in the cauſe &amp; quarrell of <hi>Cyrus, Panthaea</hi> had prepared for him a coſtly Chariot, with moſt gorgeous and glorious armour, which when he did put on, ſhe exhorted him to ſhew himſelfe a ſtout chiefetaine for <hi>Cyrus</hi> his ſake, who had bin ſo fauourable to them. With which ſpeech <hi>Abradate</hi> being highly delighted, clapping her head, and kiſſing her lippes, hee caſt his eyes vpwards to heauen, vſing theſe words: <hi>Vouchſafe great Ioue, that I may ſhew my ſelfe a husband worthy of ſuch a wife as Panthaea, &amp; a wight worthy of the frindſhip of ſuch a one as Cyrus.</hi> Who had heard this matchleſſe Lady en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage her louing husband to ſhew all poſſible proweſſe for the honor of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> or had ſeene her kiſſing the very Chariot wherein her ſweeteſt one did ſit, would haue much wondred; but much more by many degrees, who had heard her intreating, &amp; adiuring her Nurſe by her loue towards her, to ſow her vp in one winding-ſheet with her ſlaine husband: Or who had ſeene her laying his head on her lap, and powring her owne heart-bloud into his wounds: For when as <hi>Cyrus</hi> vnderſtanding of his moſt worthy friends fall in the field, fighting moſt valiantly, he vſed all the meanes he poſſible could of comforting &amp; cheering vp his peereleſſe widow <hi>Panthaea,</hi> telling her how that there ſhould bee nothing left vndone in honour of <hi>Abradate,</hi> that was due vnto a moſt valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and chiualrous Chiefetaine; and praying her to perſwade herſelfe of his moſt feruent and conſtant affection, both for <hi>Abradates</hi> ſake, and her owne, he likewiſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to tell him vnto whom ſhe had a liking to be carryed. Who anſwered; Doe not yee trouble your ſelfe, noble <hi>Cyrus,</hi> giue me but leaue a little more to be mourne my deere husband, and yee ſhall know then to whom I deſire to go, when I haue put an end to my mourning. And ſo it fell out within a few houres, that the end of her mourning, and the end of her life was all one; <hi>Abradate</hi> was the man whom ſhe loued as much as her owne ſoule, and more then all the men in the world, while he was aliue; and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date</hi> was the man whom ſhe loued more then her owne ſelfe when he was dead. In one word, it was <hi>Panthaea's</hi> death to be aliue without <hi>Abradate,</hi> and her ſweeteſt life to dye with her deere <hi>Abradate.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Panthaea</hi> thus ſhe takes her leaue, and ſayes:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adue deere One, more ſweet then Iuno's flowre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To thee moſt due; as many be thy dayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As once grew Lillies round about my bowre</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Perſian fields, and in my Lilly-towne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As many dayes weare thou the Lilly-crowne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:24"/>
            <lg n="94">
               <head>94</head>
               <l>When I <hi>Panthaea's</hi> Lilly-face behold,</l>
               <l>Her roſie lippes, her teeth of Iuory,</l>
               <l>And when I looke vpon her lockes of gold,</l>
               <l>And how her eyes are cleerer then the sky,</l>
               <l>I call to minde our <hi>Mary Clarabell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The all-grac'd Grand-dame of faire <hi>Roſimell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="95">
               <head>95</head>
               <l>Me thinkes ſhe lookes as <hi>Mary</hi> did that day</l>
               <l>The Lilly-prince did her ſo louely wed</l>
               <l>In peereleſſe <hi>Paris;</hi> ſuch as ſaw her, ſay:</l>
               <l>That nere a ſweeter Saint to Church was led</l>
               <l>In any Age, in any Land, or Clime:</l>
               <l>For of all Princes, <hi>Mary</hi> was the prime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="96">
               <head>96</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Michael Eyzin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerus</hi> in his <hi>Theſaurus prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum,</hi> moſt worthily affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that there was in this moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Queene, a gratious kinde of contention betweene good <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> which of the two ſhould beſtow moſt of their perfections vpon her princely perſon; <hi>Nature</hi> ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to heape on her head the height of exquiſite beauty; and <hi>Grace</hi> on the other part, repleniſhing her heroicall heart with the very comble and heape of vertue &amp; bounty.</note>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> did each of them contend,</l>
               <l>Which of the two ſhould moſt her magnifie;</l>
               <l>Both of them did their vtmoſt ſtrength extend</l>
               <l>Her Minde and Body for to beautifie.</l>
               <l>But her I leaue to my <hi>Muſe Clarabell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For to conclude with her childe <hi>Roſimell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:25"/>
            <lg n="97">
               <head>97</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abrinſberg</hi> is a hill on the right hand of <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> and both in the <hi>Dutch</hi> appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> records it is called S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams hill;</hi> &amp; by <hi>Trithemius</hi> it is named al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Michaels mount.</hi>
                  </note>Then viewes <hi>Eliza</hi> holy <hi>Abrah'ms</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>Which men do likewiſe tearme <hi>Saint Michaels mount,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And there (me ſeemes) an Angels quire doth fill</l>
               <l>Their eares with aires, euen ſuch as they were wont</l>
               <l>To warble forth, when ſoules from ſinfull wayes,</l>
               <l>Turne to the path that leades to paradice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="98">
               <head>98</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abrah'm</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> there do ſeeme to meet,</l>
               <l>Ioynt hand in hand as marryed folkes befits.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fred'ricke</hi> and his <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to greet,</l>
               <l>And then a while both downe beſide them ſits,</l>
               <l>Talking of duties betweene man and wife,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Of the ardent and conſtant loue that ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man &amp; wife, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed more amply in his <hi>Golden Legends</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> &amp; <hi>Sara, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Rebecca, Iacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Rahel,</hi> vpon which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her Grace to beſtow the reading ſome while agoe.</note>How they ſhould ſhun all iealouſie and ſtrife:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="99">
               <head>99</head>
               <l>Then bleſſe they them with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and his mate</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rebecca</hi> lou'd, whom beauty did commend,</l>
               <l>But bounty more; they wiſh a happy fate</l>
               <l>Vnto them both, with life that may not end,</l>
               <l>Till many yeares them and their ſeed do crowne,</l>
               <l>With higheſt hap amidſt the Mirtle-towne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="100">
               <head>100</head>
               <l>Liue Princely-paire in health and honour ſtill,</l>
               <l>Liue Princely-paire in concord, peace, and loue,</l>
               <l>Liue Princely-paire to grace your <hi>Abrah'ms</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>Till yee exchang't with <hi>Abrah'ms</hi> hill aboue.</l>
               <l>Be honour'd all your dayes, and after death,</l>
               <l>Be honour'd ay, <hi>Fred'ricke, Elizabeth.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:25"/>
            <head>THE SVMME OF DIVERS Pedigrees common to the two moſt Noble Princes FREDERICKE and ELIZABETH, Collected by the Authour, in Honour of their <hi>Highneſſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the common conſent, and conſtant opinion, of Hyſtorians, and Genelogians, that the <hi>Palatine</hi> Princes are lineally deſcended from glorious <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaigne,</hi> once the moſt <hi>Auguſtious</hi> Emperour of <hi>Romans</hi> &amp; <hi>Germanes,</hi> &amp; King of <hi>France,</hi> moſt Chriſtian, and it was chiefly in conſideration hereof, that they were preferred before many other Princes, &amp; Potentates of great power in <hi>Germany,</hi> in the election of the Emperour, &amp; namely before the Duke of <hi>Saxe,</hi> a Prince of great puiſſance, authority and command; notwithſtanding that both <hi>Otho</hi> the 3. Emperor, &amp; Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 5. which did ordaine the ſanction of the ſeuen Electors (according as <hi>Blondus, Polydorus, Bergomenſis, Nauclerus, Crantzius, Balaeus,</hi> and <hi>Egnatius</hi> do deliuer) were both of them Princes of the houſe of <hi>Saxe,</hi> for the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Otho,</hi> belike conſidering with himſelfe, how that hee had done a greater wrong to <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> in bereauing his race of the Golden Crowne of the Empire, by the meanes of his foreſaid Electionary ſanction or decree, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had done, when as he opened his Sepulcher, and bereft his Corps of the Golden Croſſe did hang about his neck (as <hi>Ditmarus,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in thoſe daies, doth write) for the which it is ſaid that he was in his ſleepe viſited &amp; affrighted with a reuengefull viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> menacing him with death, which ſhortly after did enſue: <hi>Otho,</hi> I ſay, conſidering the wrong afore-ſaid, done to <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> and his Race, endeauored by al meanes to yeeld them ſome competent ſatiſfaction, and
<pb facs="tcp:12855:26"/>therefore preferred the Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> being of the Imperiall bloud, and Male Race of <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Duke of <hi>Saxe,</hi> and the reſt of the Princes of the Empire, in the fore-ſaid Election. Beſides, that the firſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, which was elected by the ſeuen Electors, which was <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> being likewiſe a Prince of the <hi>Saxon</hi> bloud, and afterwards enſtiled Saint <hi>Henry,</hi> for his ſingular Piety &amp; Chaſtity, as <hi>Vrſpergenſis, Friſingenſis, Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius, Cuſpinianus,</hi> &amp; others do witneſſe, he to make yet ſome further ſatiſfaction to <hi>Charlemaignes</hi> Race, did both marry the daughter of <hi>Siffrid,</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> named <hi>Cunegunde,</hi> and did like-wiſe reſtore vnto his brother-in-law <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt of this name, Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> the Dukedome of <hi>Banier,</hi> as we learne out of <hi>Ditmarus</hi> &amp; others. And it was, no doubt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their fore-ſaid deſcent from <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuper-Imperiall priuiledge was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred vnto the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Prince, which is, as the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bul of the Emperor <hi>Charls</hi> the 4. doth beare, that he may, in ſome caſe, cite and ſummon the Emperor to appeare and anſwere before him Iudicially.</p>
            <p>And becauſe that in honor of the two moſt Noble Princes, lately maried, <hi>Frederick</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> we haue drawne diuers Pedigrees &amp; deſcents, both from glorious <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many other Emperors, &amp; Kings of diuers countries, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them both, eſpecially ſeuen; therfore mee thought it good, to exhibite vnto the readers a ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mary view of the ſame, reſeruing the more ſpeciall handling thereof to another la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and worke in Latine. In the firſt foure of the ſaid ſeuen Pedigrees, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to both the ſaid Princes, our moſt gratious Soueraigne King <hi>Iames,</hi> &amp; his moſt Noble ſon-in-law Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> are in one &amp; the ſelfe ſame degree of deſcent from the 20 Emperors, and 24. Kings therein mentioned. In the fifth Pedigree, our moſt gratious Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> and the ſaid Prince, are likewiſe in one and the ſame degree of Deſcent, From the 4. Emperours and 3. Kings therein named: And in th ſixth and ſeuenth, Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and Princeſſe <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> do happely and iointly fall into one and the ſame degree of deſcent from the Emperour and 8. Kings contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Likewiſe Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> two bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers-in-law,
<pb facs="tcp:12855:26"/>are colineally deſcended from two-borne-bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to wit, from <hi>Henry</hi> prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Saxe</hi> the elder of the two, from whom Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> is in the 15. degree; and from <hi>Otho</hi> Earle of <hi>Yorke</hi> and Emperour, the yonger brother, from whom <hi>P. Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> being likewiſe the yonger, of the ſaid two brothers-in-law, is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, both on his fathers and his mothers ſide, in the 13. and 14. degree; though, as I noted other-where, ſome do hold that he had no children by any of his wiues.</p>
            <p>The firſt of the fore-ſaid ſeuen common pedigrees con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth fifteene Emperours of <hi>Romans, Greekes,</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> with eight Kings of diuers Countries, as namely, <hi>Germanie, Bauier,</hi> (for anciently it was a Kingdome) <hi>Hungary, Boheme, Sicile,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> whereof two Kings are therein ſpecified: to wit, <hi>Edward</hi> the elder, and <hi>Henry</hi> 2. from whom <hi>P. Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> is deſcended by both his daughters; to wit, <hi>Maude</hi> the elder, married to <hi>Henry</hi> the Lyon, Duke of <hi>Saxe</hi> and <hi>Bauier,</hi> and <hi>Leonora</hi> the yonger, married to <hi>Alphonſe</hi> the 8. King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> Whereby we may ſee that like as <hi>P. Fredericke</hi> is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> ſo is King <hi>Iames</hi> likewiſe deſcended from diuers of the <hi>Germane</hi> Emperours, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the meanes of his moſt Noble mother, and the moſt Illuſtrious houſe of <hi>Loraine,</hi> whence it doth follow, that hee is capable of the Imperiall dignity, as being of the bloud of <hi>Germanie,</hi> and of the Empire.</p>
            <p>The ſecond common Pedigree, containeth fiue Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> together with ſeuen Kings of <hi>France, Hungary, Aragon, Valence,</hi> and <hi>Sicile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third common Pedigree containeth ſeuen Kings of <hi>England, Scotland, Ieruſalem, Castile, France, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile;</hi> of which number, are <hi>Edmond Ironſide,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt Kings of <hi>England,</hi> (beſides King <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. mentioned in the firſt Pedigree) together with <hi>Malcolme Cammore</hi> King of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth common Pedigree is from S. <hi>Lod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wicke,</hi> or <hi>Lewis</hi> the incomparable King of <hi>France,</hi> from whom King <hi>Iames,</hi> and Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> on their moſt Noble mothers ſide, <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Lucy-Iuliane,</hi> are lineally deſcended in one
<pb facs="tcp:12855:27"/>and the ſame degree with King <hi>Lodowick</hi> the 13. of this name, being all three in the 12 degree.</p>
            <p>The fifth pedigree containeth foure Emperors, and three Kings of <hi>Boheme,</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixth pedigree containeth ſeuen Kings of <hi>Arragon, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alence, France, Nauarre, England, Caſtile,</hi> and <hi>Leon,</hi> of which number are <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. and <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gant</hi> his ſonne, Knight of the renowned Order of the Garter, Earle of <hi>Richmond, Darby, Leiceſter,</hi> and <hi>Lincolne, Palatine</hi> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Great Conſtable of <hi>France,</hi> and High Steward of <hi>England,</hi> Duke of <hi>Aquitane</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Leon;</hi> from whom prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are lineally deſcended, the one by his ſonne. <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Sommerſet, Marquis Dorſet,</hi> the other by his daughter <hi>Philippa</hi> married to <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>Portugale,</hi> &amp; both in the tenth degree, which is the eleuenth from King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. as the pedigree I haue lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed doth ſhew.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth and laſt Pedigree common to both the ſaid Princes, is from <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the 5. Duke of <hi>Bauier</hi> and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and his wife <hi>Margaret</hi> the Empreſſe, and Counteſſe of <hi>Holland;</hi> together with King <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> from the which Emperour and Empreſſe they are both in the 12 degree. So that the number of the Emperours contained in the ſaid ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen pedigrees. common to both, falleth out to be twenty &amp; fiue; and the number of the Kings of diuers countries therin ſpecified, is thirty, and aboue; and euen ſo many Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides 12. Emperours, haue we found in the Princely deſcent of the Illuſtrious houſe of <hi>Howards,</hi> as wee ſhall (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) ſhew in another worke.</p>
            <p>One thing there is, which the ſpecial affection I do beare to the honour of the name of <hi>Iames,</hi> will not ſuffer me to ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp, and that is; That our moſt gracious Souerainge King <hi>Iames,</hi> the firſt of this name in <hi>Britanny,</hi> and likewiſe the firſt Chriſtian vniter of the two kingdomes therof, and the ſon &amp; heire of a Matchleſſe Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> together with his Noble ſon-in-law, <hi>P. Fredericke</hi> are both of them in the 13. degree of lineall deſcent from <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt of this name, ſurnamed
<pb facs="tcp:12855:27"/>the <hi>Fortunate,</hi> ſon and heire of a worthy Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and the vniting King of <hi>Aragon</hi> and <hi>Valence,</hi> of whom ſix famous <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Chroniclers, <hi>Rodericus Toletanus, Rodericus Sanctius, Alphonſus à Carthagena, Franciſcus Tarapha, Lucius Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> and <hi>Damianus à Goes</hi> make moſt honourable mention. And from the ſame vniting King of <hi>Aragon, Iames the Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> who was likewiſe the Author of two ſeuerall Orders of Knighthood (as <hi>Polydorus, Zuingerus,</hi> and others do write) Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> are yet another way lineally deſcended, and that both in one &amp; the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, of the number of fifteene. It is likewiſe worthy of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, that whereas there haue beene but only two Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Family he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e; the one a yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother, and Duke of <hi>Baui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lodowicke</hi> the 5. the other an elder brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ount Palatine,</hi> which was <hi>Robert,</hi> ſurnamed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the two Princes lately mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, are deſcended equally from them both, with their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes, <hi>Margaret</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> from the firſt two, both in the 12 degree; and from the other two, He in the 9. &amp; She in the 10 degree. And my hearty wiſh is, that theſe two names aforeſaid, <hi>Margaret</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> may proue as lucky Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially, for <hi>Frederickes</hi> and <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Imperiall preferment in <hi>Germany,</hi> as the ſame names haue heretofore done royally for King <hi>Iames</hi> their fathers royall preferment in <hi>Britanny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo worth the noting, that as there haue beene as yet but only two Emperours of the <hi>Palatine</hi> family, ſo haue they had a very different fortune in their acceptance towards the Pope; for <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the 5. Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> and Emperour, as is ſaid before, from whom <hi>Prince Fredericke</hi> is the 12, was highly hated of <hi>Benedict</hi> the 12, and before him, yet more, of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22 (whoſe name is ſo numerous, that he might haue well ſaid with the vncleane ſpirit in the Goſpell, my name is <hi>Legion</hi>) and yet after him of a third pope, <hi>Clement</hi> the 6. The which three popes (moſt like the three Furies) did no other thing elſe, from day to day, but heape helliſh ſentence vpon ſentence of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication &amp; depriuation againſt the good Emperour; who not withſtanding all their <hi>Infernall</hi> fulmina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and <hi>Cerbereall</hi> oblatrations, receiued more honour in
<pb facs="tcp:12855:28"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> at the hands of both Clergy &amp; Laity there, then they all three did in <hi>Auinion;</hi> and in ſpite of the Diuell, liued lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the Empire, then they all three did in the Papacy. But who liſt to learne more of the quarrels and contentions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the good Emperour <hi>Lodowike,</hi> and the foreſaid three euill popes of <hi>Auinion,</hi> let them read the hiſtories of <hi>Blondus, Sabellicus, Merula, Cuſpinianus,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Walſingham,</hi> who likewiſe do tell, how that <hi>Edward</hi> the third, King of <hi>England,</hi> who went ouer into <hi>Germany</hi> to ſalute the ſaid Emperour, &amp; to treat of an alliance with him againſt <hi>France,</hi> was met of the ſaid Emperour at <hi>Colein,</hi> and admitted to be his Vicar ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in the Empire. And the ſame <hi>Lodowickes</hi> father, named <hi>Lodowicke the Seuere,</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> together with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Henry,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauier,</hi> had likewiſe choſen <hi>Richard,</hi> Earle of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> ſon of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> to be Emperour; like as <hi>Robert</hi> the firſt of this name, Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> (for this Title is in <hi>Aurea Bulla</hi> as well as that of <hi>Count Palatine</hi>) did chooſe the foreſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, to be Emperour after the death of <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the 5. though hee (too modeſtly indeed) refuſed the ſaid dignity. By which particulars wee may eſpy how that the <hi>Palatine</hi> Princes haue been in former times very officious to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and their children; hoping that they ſhall hereafter proue yet more officious &amp; forward in the ſame kind, then euer they haue done before, to the end that old propheſies may take effect, which doe promiſe, that the Imperiall dignity ſhall for many yeares continue in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanny,</hi> as our <hi>Sibylla Britannica</hi> ſhall largely ſhew.</p>
            <p>The other Emperour of the <hi>Palatine</hi> houſe, was <hi>Robert,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the <hi>Noble,</hi> who reigned in great honor, 9 yeares and 9 moneths, from whom prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> is the 9.) as the pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree lately publiſhed doth ſhew) and who was ſo highly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 9. that hee not onely furthered and confirmed his election, but alſo granted him, towards a ſubſidy, one yeares tythes of the Clergy, through all <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> as <hi>Cuſpinianus</hi> and others do write. So that this good Pope in doing this good office, and in vſing ſo well the worthy Emperour, did anſwere to his name, and was a <hi>Boniface</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, farre otherwiſe then did <hi>Benedictus</hi> the 12. and <hi>Clement</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12855:28"/>the 6 in the behalfe of the other <hi>Palatine</hi> Emperour named before. And for mine owne part, I wiſh with all my heart that many ſuch Biſhops may ſit in the Apoſtolicall Chaire, as may both in their own perſons giue vnto God the things that are Gods, &amp; vnto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars;</hi> and with bleſſed S. <hi>Peter,</hi> teach all Chriſtians to feare God, &amp; honor the King. The foreſaid <hi>Robert</hi> the good Emperour, &amp; who was ſo highly beloued of the good pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 9. was a prince renowned for his great ſpirit, quicke wit, heroicall courage, for his loue and ſtudy of Iuſtice, (for the which cauſe he was ſurnamed <hi>Robertus Iuſtimanus</hi>) &amp; for his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full endeuouring to repaire the ancient glory of the Empire. Hee came into <hi>England</hi> with a goodly company (as <hi>Fabian</hi> &amp; <hi>Cooper</hi> do write) in the yeare 1403. to ſee the magnificence of the Court, and the commodities of the Countrey, who of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. was honorably &amp; triumphantly receiued &amp; feaſted; and during his abode lodged at S. <hi>Iohns</hi> by <hi>Smithfield:</hi> &amp; laſtly conueyed towards the ſeaſide, where either departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other with exchange of rich &amp; pretious gifts: for this <hi>Robert</hi> (ſaith our ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Author) was a prince of great bounty, liberality, and magnificence, and ſhewed diuers effects thereof towards the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at his departure. He was likewiſe the firſt Emperor that euer ware S. <hi>Georges</hi> renowned or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, commonly called, <hi>The Order of the Garter,</hi> as <hi>Maximilian</hi> the 2. another glorious Emperour was the eighth. He was likewiſe the firſt of the three <hi>Palatines,</hi> which haue ben honored with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid noble Order; <hi>Iohn Caſimire</hi> being the ſecond, who receiued it at the hands of famous Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> about the ſame time of the yeare, &amp; day of the moneth, (to wit, the 8. of February) that <hi>P. Fredericke</hi> being the third, receiued it at the hands of our gracious K. <hi>Iames.</hi> The ſaid Emperor <hi>Roberts</hi> wife was named <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Empreſſe, &amp; princeſſe <hi>Palatine,</hi> and was a Lady of ſingular vertue, piety, bounty, chaſtity &amp; charity towards the poore; who brought forth to her worthy husband many fine children, to wit, fiue ſons, by the meanes of the yongeſt whereof, <hi>P. Fredericke</hi> is deſcended from the ſaid Emperor &amp; Empres in the 9. degree; &amp; three daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by the meanes of the eldeſt wherof, named <hi>Margaret,</hi> princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is likewiſe deſcended from them in the 10 degree; the which numbers in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnited, make vp K. <hi>Iames</hi> his luckly number of <hi>Nineteene.</hi> Thus wee ſee; that like as our moſt gracious King
<pb facs="tcp:12855:29"/>
               <hi>Iames,</hi> with his hopefull children, prince <hi>Charles,</hi> &amp; princeſſe <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> are lineally deſcended from two <hi>Margarets,</hi> and one <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Britany,</hi> being the renowned daughters of prince <hi>Edward,</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Outlaw:</hi> K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. and K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. in whoſe trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led right (the two <hi>Margarets</hi> being married to two kings of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Malcolme Cammore,</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> the 4.) he doth at this day hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily and rightfully enioy this Crowne. So are they likewiſe deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded lineally from other two <hi>Margarets</hi> &amp; an <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> to wit, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Margaret</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Holland,</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Bauier,</hi> &amp; Empreſſe, wife to <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the Emperour, from <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Bauier,</hi> princeſſe <hi>Palatine,</hi> and Empreſſe, wife to <hi>Robert</hi> the Emperour: and ſuſtly, from <hi>Margaret,</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Loraine,</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt daughter of the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Empreſſe, and who was married to the moſt noble and valorous prince <hi>Charles,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Marcelle,</hi> or the warlike Duke of <hi>Loraine,</hi> from whom I haue deriued our hopefull <hi>P. Charles</hi> his pedigree; and that as well on his noble mothers as on his happy fathers ſide, and yet more from Emperours, Kings and Princes of the name of <hi>Charles,</hi> to the number of 9. beſides thoſe of other names, as alſo I haue done from <hi>P. Albert,</hi> Marquiſe of <hi>Brandeburge,</hi> who for his incomparable courage was called the <hi>Achilles of Germany;</hi> wiſhing with all my heart, that like as prince <hi>Charles</hi> was borne on his day, &amp; doth participate of his bloud, ſo he may likewiſe inherit his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical proweſſe, and ſo one day be enſtiled the <hi>Achilles of Britanny:</hi> the which our hearty wiſh is more fully expreſſed in an Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall and Hiſtoricall poem made vpon his <hi>Natiuity.</hi> And thus for the preſent are we contented to ſhut vp this Genealogicall ſumme with this ſix-line-Epigram, in honour of <hi>Fredericke</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whom the God of heauen proſper and preſerue.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Both from <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Auguſta</hi> ſpring</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lodwicke-Margret, Robert-Elizabeth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both in one month <hi>Ioue</hi> to the light did bring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> nam'd, which this good preſage hath:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>AVGVSTVS</hi> fate one day muſt them befall,</l>
               <l>And him <hi>AVGVSTVS,</hi> her <hi>AVGVSTA</hi> call.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12855:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
